<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Forgery no Christianity, or, A brief examen of a late book published by one T. Plant, a Baptist teacher, under the title of A contest for Christianity, or, A faithful relation of two late meetings &amp;c. as also some animadversions on J. Ives's postscript and an expostulatory postscript to the Baptists / by Thomas Ellwood.</title>
            <author>Ellwood, Thomas, 1639-1713.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 205KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 70 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B21656</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11081425</idno>
  <idno type="VID">204828</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240890932</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing E621</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">11081425</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B21656)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 204828)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1423:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Forgery no Christianity, or, A brief examen of a late book published by one T. Plant, a Baptist teacher, under the title of A contest for Christianity, or, A faithful relation of two late meetings &amp;c. as also some animadversions on J. Ives's postscript and an expostulatory postscript to the Baptists / by Thomas Ellwood.</title>
                  <author>Ellwood, Thomas, 1639-1713.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>139 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1674.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Plant, Thomas. --  Contest for Christianity.</term>
               <term type="personal_name">Ives, Jeremiah, fl. 1653-1674.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Society of Friends --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Baptists --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>Simon Charles </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:204828:1"/>
            <p>FORGERY NO Christianity: Or, a Brief EXAMEN Of a late Book, published by one <hi>T. Plant,</hi> a <hi>Baptist-Teacher,</hi> under the Title of <hi>A Contest for Christianity,</hi> or, <hi>A Faithful Relation of Two late Meetings, &amp;c.</hi> As also, Some Animadversions on <hi>J. Ives</hi>'s POSTSCRIPT. And an Expostulatory Postscript to the BAPTISTS.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Thomas Ellwood.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Jer. 9.5.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>They will deceive every one his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and will not speak the Truth: they have taught their Tongues to speak Lyes, and weary themselves to commit Iniquity.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Isa. 54.17.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>No Weapon that is formed against thee shall prosper; &amp; every tongue that shal rise against thee in Judgment, thou shalt condemn.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Year 1674.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:204828:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:204828:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THat which I here present unto thy view, is a brief Examen of a late Book, publish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by one <hi>Thomas Plant,</hi> under the specious Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of a <hi>Contest for Christianity;</hi> wherein he pretends to give a Faithful Relation of Two late Meetings, between the <hi>Baptists</hi> and the <hi>Quakers:</hi> And that his Title might end as plausibly as it begun, it is <hi>submitted to the Judgment of all Judicious and Impartial Men;</hi> with this Addition, <hi>Read, Consider, Examine and then Judge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Three Parts of Four, of the Liberty given, I have taken; to <hi>read, consider, examine,</hi> and there stopt, reserving the judicial part to thee. Had my Opponent done so too (as well as said it) thou hadst had a fuller Account, and we fairer Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling from him. But I have no Design to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>occupy thy Judgment, which by how much the freer it is, and less susceptible of private Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presses,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:204828:3"/> by so much the more capable it is of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing a just and even Sentence, which is all I desire at thy Hand: yet two or three Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars I am willing to give thee a short Hint of, and that rather in this place then in the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Treatise it self.</p>
            <p n="1">1<hi>st,</hi> Concerning the Title of my Opponent's Book, viz. <hi>A Contest for Christianity.</hi> A very fair and glittering Title, set out, as it were on purpose to draw in Guests. But as <hi>Good Wine</hi> (according to the Proverb) <hi>needs no Bush;</hi> and <hi>the Best Accommodations are not alwayes found in those Inns which hang out the fairest Signs;</hi> so neither wilt thou find any thing in his Book which may bear proportion to his lofty Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle. The Book it self begins with a Charge, exhibited by the <hi>Quakers</hi> against one of the <hi>Baptists,</hi> containing Matter of <hi>Forgery, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versions, Lyes</hi> and <hi>Slanders:</hi> This was the proper Subject of those Meetings; but this they would not come to the Test of, but thrust us by with a rude Clamour that we are <hi>No Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans:</hi> Of this he pretends to give a Relation, and mis-calls it, <hi>A Contest for Christianity:</hi> How much more truly and aptly might he have called it, <hi>A Cover for Forgery,</hi> since their chief Design and Aim was, to divert us
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:204828:3"/> from the Proof of that Charge, whereof <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery</hi> was the greatest part: To shew him there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Mistake, in thinking he contended for <hi>Christianity,</hi> I chuse to let the following Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise bear this Title, <hi>Forgery No Christianity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Concerning the Time of its Publication; it was about Two Moneths after the last of those Meetings, before their <hi>Relation</hi> was made publick; which (if I apprehend aright) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces not at all to its Reputation, but rather gives Ground to suspect the Truth of it, and call its Credit into Question: For, if (as is pretended) it was taken in Short-Hand at the Meeting, what need so long an Interval for the transcribing of Half a Dozen Sheets. I leave it therefore to thy Consideration, Whether the Reason of this needless Delay was not, that they might have time to Cabal about it, to lay their heads together, &amp; consult how they might model it most to their Advantage; and by comparing it with those which we had before published, to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve what to alter, what to add, what wholely to expunge, and what to transpose or transplace, that thereby they might be sure to thwart the Accounts we had given, and make their own speak as loud for themselves as they pleased.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:204828:4"/>
            <p n="3">3. Concerning my present Ʋndertaking; I am not ignorant, that to invalidate another's Relation, is a Work of some Difficulty; since it is not enough that I my self know it to be False, unless I am also able to disprove it: To urge my own Personal Knowledge, would be but (with <hi>T. Plant</hi>) to make my self Judge: To compare it with our own Relation, and from the Disparity infer it False, I judge not fair nor reasonable, but blame our Adversaries for dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling so with us: To produce Testimonies of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons then present, would be uncertain and inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cisive, since it might either be questioned, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Persons were impartial; or doubted, whether their Memories were sufficiently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentive: I have taken that way which I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive to be clearest and freest from Objection, viz. <hi>To Oppose the Relation to it self, and by such Instances as I could gather from it self, to manifest and demonstrate to thy Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing, that it is Imperfect, Partial and False.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, as I have chosen to steer this Course in a modest Respect to thee, that I might not, without some kind of Demonstration, obtrude my Sence upon thy Belief (as my Adversary too confidently and frequently doth his) so I must
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:204828:4"/> request of thee, That thou wilt not think, much less conclude, that the Exceptions which I shall now offer thee, are all I can justly make against their <hi>Relation;</hi> or that I allow those parts of it as True, against which I have not here par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly excepted: but that I therefore offer thee these Exceptions (not because these are the only, nor perhaps the most weighty, that might be given, but) because these are the most obvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and easie to be evidenced: For, I speak considerately, I do really think there are not many Pages in the whole, which, in one respect or other, either for Adding, Diminishing, Transposing or Perverting, may not justly be excepted against.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>T. E.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:204828:5"/>
            <p>BEfore I enter upon the Book it self, I judge it necessary to premise the Method I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to observe therein, which is this:
<list>
                  <item>I. A brief Account of the Occasion and Subject of these Meetings.</item>
                  <item>II. My Exceptions against <hi>Tho. Plant</hi>'s <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation</hi> of them, as being not faithfully, but imperfectly, partially and falsly given.</item>
                  <item>III. Some Observations on the most material Passages in his Relation, including also his Marginal Notes.</item>
                  <item>IV. Some Animadversions upon <hi>Jer. Ives</hi>'s <hi>Postscript.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>V. A Postscript to all Conscientious <hi>Baptists.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:204828:5"/>
            <head>Forgery No Christianity.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. A brief Account of the Occasion and Subject of these Meetings.</head>
               <p>THe Occasion of these Meetings, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginally, I take to be those <hi>Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logues,</hi> which were written and published by <hi>Thomas Hicks,</hi> to <hi>traduce and defame our Principles and Ʋs:</hi> of which <hi>Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> we being sensible, complained to the <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tists</hi> against their Brother, and called upon them <hi>to do us Justice.</hi> They thereupon, in a Meeting of <hi>their own</hi> appointing at <hi>Barbican,</hi> took an Opportunity, <hi>in our Absence,</hi> to call <hi>T. Hicks</hi> to an Account, as they pretended, and (as far as in them lay) <hi>acquitted</hi> him of those <hi>Crimes</hi> which we had <hi>justly</hi> charged up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him. This gave us Cause of new <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint,</hi> not only against him, but them, by whom we had been thus <hi>surprized.</hi> And
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:204828:6"/> hereupon we demanded of them a Publick Meeting, to be appointed by mutual Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, wherein we might personally exhibit and make good our Charge against <hi>T. Hicks,</hi> and he personally make his Defence.</p>
               <p>This, in short, concerning the Occasion. Now as briefly also as well I can, concerning the Subject of these Meetings.</p>
               <p>In the <hi>Epistle</hi> before their <hi>Relation, T. Plant</hi> tells his Reader, That <hi>In Pursuance of</hi> W. P<hi>'s Offer for a Publick Meeting, several of our Friends and theirs met to discourse thereabout; but they could not agree touching the Matter to be insisted on.</hi> Whereupon he sayes, <hi>A Paper was delivered to our Friends to be communicated to</hi> W. P. <hi>and</hi> G. W. which sayes he, is as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="inline">Whereas there are divers things charged by <hi>W. Penn</hi> &amp; <hi>G. Whitehead</hi> against <hi>T. Hicks</hi> in two Books, one intituled, <hi>Reason against Railing;</hi> the other, <hi>The Counterfeit Christian detected;</hi> intimating, as if the said <hi>T. Hicks had wrong'd the People call'd</hi> Quakers, <hi>by For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery, Lying and false Quotations.</hi> And where as the said <hi>W. P.</hi> and <hi>G.W.</hi> or some other of the <hi>Quakers,</hi> did appeal to sober People, but especially to the <hi>Baptists,</hi> to hear and examine whether the said T. H. <hi>was guilty of the said
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:204828:6"/> Accusations or not.</hi> And a Meting being therupon appointed, wherein the <hi>said Charge</hi> was examined; we are fully satisfied that in all these material Things, then insisted upon, <hi>T. H.</hi> hath done them no Wrong, &amp;c.</q>
               </p>
               <p>This Paper is subscribed by
<q>
                     <list>
                        <item>W. Kiffin,</item>
                        <item>T. Paul,</item>
                        <item>D. Dike,</item>
                        <item>T. Plant.</item>
                     </list>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>The Reason (Reader) why I have transcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed so much of this Paper of theirs, is, That thou mayst see and understand <hi>from their own Confession,</hi> what <hi>they themselves</hi> understood to be the <hi>Ground</hi> and <hi>Occasion</hi> of <hi>our Appeal; what</hi> it was <hi>they</hi> appointed <hi>their</hi> Meeting for, and <hi>what</hi> it was <hi>they took upon them</hi> to hear and examine, viz. FORGERY, LYING <hi>and</hi> FALSE QUOTATIONS. FORGERY then <hi>by their own Confession,</hi> was that <hi>we complained</hi> of, and demanded <hi>Justice</hi> of them for: FOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GERY then, <hi>by their own Confession,</hi> was that they <hi>appointed</hi> their <hi>Meeting</hi> to <hi>Examine:</hi> FORGERY then, <hi>by their own Confession,</hi> was the <hi>Business</hi> depending between <hi>them and us.</hi> By this, Reader, thou must here take notice, that FORGERY was indeed the <hi>proper Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject</hi> to have been <hi>discoursed</hi> between <hi>them</hi> and <hi>us,</hi> at those late <hi>Meetings,</hi> which we have had together: What Shifting and Shuffling? what
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:204828:7"/> Twisting and Twining? what Tricks and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices were used by them to avoid this <hi>Theam,</hi> thou shalt also see anon.</p>
               <p>Let this suffice to be spoken in this Place, of the Occasion and Subject of these Meetings. Let me now shew <hi>T. Plant</hi> one of his Mistakes, and so proceed to the next Head.</p>
               <p>In his <hi>Epistle</hi> he tells his Reader, That <hi>The Answer to the</hi> Quakers Appeal <hi>being publisht,</hi> W. Penn <hi>thereupon published a Complaint a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst it, in which he was pleased to make an Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer for another Publick Meeting.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here I must desire <hi>T.P.</hi> to <hi>recollect</hi> his <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory,</hi> &amp; then I doubt not but he will find <hi>him self under</hi> a very great <hi>mistake.</hi> He makes their publishing of their <hi>Answer</hi> to the <hi>Quakers Appeal,</hi> to be not only before <hi>W. Penn</hi>'s <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint</hi> and <hi>Offer</hi> of a Publick Meeting, but also to be the Ground and Occasion of that <hi>Complaint</hi> and <hi>Offer, which is indeed utterly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>true;</hi> for it was, I think, well nigh a <hi>Month</hi> after their first Meeting at <hi>Barbican,</hi> before their Book call'd <hi>The</hi> Quakers <hi>Appeal answered,</hi> came forth; whereas <hi>W. P</hi>'s <hi>Complaint</hi> against them, and <hi>Offer</hi> of a Publick Meeting, was published within <hi>eight</hi> Dayes after that Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as by the Date of each will appear, the one being the 28th of <hi>August,</hi> the other the 5th of <hi>September.</hi> Besides, in that very Book
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:204828:7"/> of theirs, call'd <hi>The</hi> Quakers <hi>Appeal answer'd,</hi> they take notice of this Complaint of <hi>W. P</hi>'s, <hi>Epist.</hi> p. 9. in these Words: <q rend="inline">
                     <hi>And whereas there is a late Paper printed by Way of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint of several scandalous Reports in City and Country against <hi>W. P.</hi> and <hi>G. W.</hi> as if they purposely neglected to meet the Day afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </q> Again in the Postscript, p. 32. thus, <q rend="inline">
                     <hi>Having seen <hi>W.P</hi>'s Complaint, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in—he is pleased to propose for a Publick Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </q> This puts it beyond all Doubt, that <hi>W. Penn</hi>'s Complaint and Offer of a Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Meeting, was published before their Book call'd <hi>The</hi> Quakers <hi>Appeal answered;</hi> and consequently, That <hi>T. Plant mistook his Notes,</hi> in making their Book antecedent to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint, and to be the Ground and Cause of it. However, though I might here say of <hi>T. Plant, In ipso limine cadit, he stumbles,</hi> as it were, <hi>at the very Entrance:</hi> Yet I will not extend it further, then to a <hi>Weakness</hi> of his Memory, or his <hi>Inadvertency</hi> in Writing.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:204828:8"/>
               <head>CHAP. II. My Exceptions against <hi>T. Plant</hi>'s Relation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Having in the former Chapter briefly hint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Occasion and Subject of those <hi>Meetings,</hi> of which <hi>T. Plant</hi> pretends to give <hi>A Relation;</hi> my next Work is, to exhibit my <hi>Exceptions</hi> against the Relation which he hath given; in which I shall endeavour to demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate to the Reader, that <hi>THAT Relation</hi> (though pretended to be <hi>Faithful</hi>) is indeed <hi>Partial, Defective &amp; False:</hi> In Order where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto I premise this, That, <hi>Whosoever under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taketh to give a faithful Relation of a mutual Discourse or Conference, ought indifferently &amp; equally to deliver the Speeches and Sayings of each Party, according as they themselves spake them, not designedly adding to the one, nor sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stracting from the other, much less concealing or perverting the Answers of either; otherwise his Relation cannot be faithful and true:</hi> But that <hi>Tho. Plant</hi> in the Relation which he hath pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished, hath <hi>not indifferently and equally</hi> deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered the Speeches and Sayings of each Party, according as they spake them, but hath <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal'd</hi>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:204828:8"/> many of their <hi>Answers;</hi> and consequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that <hi>his Relation is not faithful and true,</hi> let the following <hi>Exceptions</hi> be throughly consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered.</p>
               <p>After <hi>Tho. Plant</hi> hath brought his Brother <hi>Hicks</hi> no less then 7. <hi>pages</hi> on his way in one entire &amp; uninterrupted Answer, and was lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him on, how much further, I know not: He tells his Reader <hi>pag.</hi> 21. <q rend="inline">
                     <hi>Here <hi>W. Penn,</hi> and others of his Friends interrupted, and took up much Time about other matters, running from this first unto the third Charge, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Except.</hi> 1.</label> In this I except against the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation as <hi>Defective,</hi> and tax the Relator with <hi>Partiality:</hi> for he ought to have faithfully set down the particular Discourse, as it passed, whether to him it seem'd pertinent or not, that his Reader (to whom of Right it belong'd) might himself have been Judge of the matter, and not be oblieged to take it upon trust from him, who in all Probability did therefore omit it, because his Account was imperfect and faulty; or finding that it made against him and his Party, chose rather (which is worse) to conceal it. Could he find in his Heart to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain his Reader with so <hi>prolix a Discourse</hi> against us, and yet think much to give him <hi>one Line</hi> of what we replied thereto? He sayes, <hi>We took up much Time:</hi> from whence may be
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:204828:9"/> inferr'd, that <hi>much was spoaken.</hi> Now whether his be a true Relation, which of that <hi>Much</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates <hi>Nothing,</hi> I leave, <hi>Reader,</hi> to thy Consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration; and trace him further.</p>
               <p>He goes on thus, <hi>p.</hi> 22. <q rend="inline">
                     <hi>But W. Penn see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that no Answer would be given to those things till the first Article was concluded, He then with others of his Assistents, for a conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable time insisted upon the Form of Writing, pretending, as if this were their chief Quarrel with <hi>T. Hicks</hi> under this first Head.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Except.</hi> 2.</label> Herein the Relator hath been greatly to blame: <hi>He promiseth fair, performs nothing less.</hi> In his Title page he proposeth a <hi>faithful</hi> Relation; in his Preface, a <hi>faithful</hi> Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, &amp; that <hi>submitted</hi> to the Judgment of all Judicious and Impartial Men: But what is here for such to Judge? <hi>He himself has before hand judged, concluded and determined the Matter: We insisted</hi> (he sayes) <hi>on the Form of Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, pretending as if that were our chief Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel against</hi> T. Hicks: But <hi>in what Manner</hi> was this insisted on? What <hi>Objections</hi> were offered <hi>against</hi> that Form of Writing? What Reasons or Arguments to <hi>confirm</hi> those Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions? <hi>Not a Word of this;</hi> and yet he calls his Relation <hi>faithful.</hi> Surely, if we insisted on it, as <hi>our chief Quarrel,</hi> and that too (as he saith) for a <hi>considerable time, something</hi> must
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:204828:9"/> needs have been spoaken of it; how then can his Relation be <hi>faithful,</hi> which gives the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>not one Word</hi> of what we spake concerning it? Will he say, It was Impertinent; <hi>Who made him Judge?</hi> Was it not enough for him to be a <hi>partial</hi> Relator, unless he were also an <hi>Ʋnjust</hi> Judge? Did he affect Brevity; What made him then so <hi>Tedious</hi> but just before in relating at large <hi>T. Hicks</hi>'s long winded Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion against us?</p>
               <p>He goes on thus: <q rend="inline">
                     <hi>But this being fully an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer'd, at least to the Satisfaction of all the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial Hearers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Except.</hi> 3.</label> Here again the Relation is <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fective,</hi> and the Relator extreamly <hi>partial.</hi> The one defective, in <hi>omitting</hi> this full An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer; the other partial, in undertaking to <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine,</hi> that the Answer was full; and much more so, in affirming, That it was <hi>satisfactory to all the Impartial Hearers:</hi> What room, I pray, hath he here left for any judicious man <hi>to exercise his Judgment</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> how shall the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der be able to judge, whether what we insisted on was <hi>fully</hi> answer'd, when he neither knows what the Answers were; nor, whether indeed there were any, or no? But how knows <hi>Tho. Plant</hi> that <hi>the Answers were satisfactory to all the impartial Hearers?</hi> Did <hi>All</hi> that were im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial express their Satisfaction? And is he
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:204828:10"/> well assured, that <hi>All</hi> they who did so express, were in very deed impartial? Why did he not insert these Answers in his Relation, that they might have been as satisfactory to <hi>All</hi> impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Readers, as he saith, <hi>they were to</hi> All <hi>impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Hearers?</hi> What Reason can be suppos'd for this Omission? Doubtless, he will not say, <hi>These Answers were impertinent both as they were given by</hi> his own Party, <hi>and as himself here declares them full and satisfactory.</hi> But, hast thou not Cause, <hi>Reader,</hi> to suspect, that he was really <hi>conscious</hi> of the <hi>Weakness and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>validity</hi> of these Answers, and therefore would not venture to <hi>submit</hi> them to thy Judgment, but chose rather to pass them <hi>hastily</hi> over, and <hi>obtrude his Sence</hi> upon thy Belief? However, this is obvious, that <hi>some</hi> Answers he <hi>confesses</hi> were given, yet his Relation gives <hi>None;</hi> but instead thereof, he takes upon him to <hi>deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine,</hi> that those Answers were <hi>full</hi> and <hi>satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factory.</hi> Whether this be <hi>consistent</hi> with a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and impartial Relation, I leave to the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der's Judgment, and proceed.</p>
               <p>In <hi>pag.</hi> 24, 25. <hi>Jer. Ives</hi> proposeth a Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion, <q rend="inline">
                     <hi>Whether the Human Nature be a part of the true Christ of God now in Heaven ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Intercession for us? <hi>whereunto says</hi> T.P. We could gain no direct Answer.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Except.</hi> 4.</label> Hence I again except against the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:204828:10"/> Relation as unfairly, unfaithfully and partially written. <hi>T. Plant</hi> confesseth, an <hi>Answer</hi> was given; but saith, it was not <hi>direct</hi> to the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion: Why did not he (as became a Relator) give that Answer, whatever it was, to his Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that his Reader might judge how direct and proper the Answer was to the Question? How fain would he lead his Reader blindfold, or perswade him to see with his Eyes, not with his own! But, Oh faithless, O shameless Man! With what Face canst thou call this a faithful Relation, which thy own Conscience knows to be so false and faulty? How couldst thou judge it fair, that thy self, <hi>being a Party,</hi> and so immediately concern'd as thou art, shouldst <hi>conceal</hi> our Answer from the Reader, and take upon thee to tell him, it was <hi>not direct?</hi> Much better mightst thou have submitted thy Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the <hi>Belief</hi> of the <hi>Credulous,</hi> then to the <hi>Judgment</hi> of the <hi>Judicious;</hi> since the first Sort might perhaps have <hi>Implicitely acquiesced</hi> in thy Judgment, and have taken thy Report <hi>upon Trust;</hi> whereas the latter have no Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to <hi>exercise</hi> their Judgments on, unless it be to <hi>censure thy Ʋnjust Dealings.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Sum of my Exceptions against this Part of the Relation is, That it's very <hi>defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive and imperfect,</hi> and the Relator therein most <hi>Ʋnfaithful</hi> to us, and <hi>Abusive</hi> of his
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:204828:11"/> Reader; for he hath dropt well nigh <hi>a Dozen</hi> Pages together of the Discourse that passed between them &amp; us, and instead thereof hath, in about <hi>so many</hi> Lines, given the Reader an Account in <hi>general,</hi> what in his Judgment was the Issue of it. But let the Relator remember, and the Reader consider well that Maxim, <hi>sub generalibus latet dolus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Three <hi>Instances</hi> more, by way of <hi>Exception,</hi> I offer to the Reader's Consideration.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That of all the Discourse that passed that Day between them and us, the Answers that they have given in <hi>our</hi> Names (if they were all put together) will amount to but about 16 Lines, whereas the Relation itself containeth in the whole about 12 pages, of which no less then 7 are spent in one Answer of <hi>T. Hicks:</hi> Let the Reader, I say, but observe this, <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>T. Hicks singly</hi> takes up of their Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, 7 <hi>pages</hi> in one Answer, and that the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swers of <hi>All</hi> the <hi>Quakers</hi> that spoak there (as they are set down in that Relation) being <hi>All</hi> put together, will hardly make up 16 Lines; and then let him judge whether that be a fair, an honest, a faithful Relation, as <hi>T. Plant</hi> calls it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That such Passages as were spoaken by any of themselves, and proved offensive to the Auditors, are wholy left out of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:204828:11"/> as if there had been no such Thing spoa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken; particularly, that unseemly Expression of <hi>J. Ives,</hi> when he call'd the <hi>dead Body of Christ a Carcass;</hi> which, because it was ill resented by the Auditory, is not to be found in their Relation.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That they have not only <hi>left out</hi> our Part of the Discourse, but that they might so do, have also <hi>dropt one of their own Disputants,</hi> namely, <hi>R. Forguson,</hi> a <hi>Presbyterian,</hi> who in that Part of the Dispute, which they have <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted,</hi> bestir'd himself in <hi>T. Hicks</hi>'s Defence. And truly, though his Endeavours proved in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>successful, they have no Reason to be ashamed of the Man (though of either craving or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting his Help, they have) whose Unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piness it was to espouse <hi>a bad Cause,</hi> being much more able in Point of Learning, to have defended it, then themselves, <hi>if it had been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fensible.</hi> But leaving them to give the World an Account of their engaging <hi>so many contrary Interests</hi> against us, I shall only here desire the Reader seriously to consider, whether in rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a mutual Discourse or Dispute, the <hi>leaving out</hi> a great Part of what was spoaken, and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealing</hi> withall the Names of the Persons speaking, be the <hi>Property</hi> of an <hi>Impartial</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lator, or <hi>consistent</hi> with a <hi>faithful</hi> Account, as <hi>T. Plant,</hi> notwithstanding all these <hi>Omissions,</hi> hath the <hi>Confidence</hi> to call his.</p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:204828:12"/>
               <p>Let these Exceptions suffice against the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the first Meeting; and let us now Reader, a little examine the Account that is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of the second, which, though it be said to be written by one <hi>T. Jennings</hi> (a Person I have no Knowledge of) yet inasmuch as this is pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished, as well as the former by <hi>T. Plant,</hi> and by him recommended as faithful, I hope he will have no Cause, to think I deal hardly with him, if I place the Defects and Errors of this to his Accompt also. To begin therefore.</p>
               <p>In p. 74. <hi>J. Ives</hi> sayes, <q rend="inline">
                     <hi>I will prove out of several of your Writings that call your selves <hi>Quakers,</hi> that you are no <hi>Christians.</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </q> To this they make <hi>G. Whitehead</hi> answer thus, <q rend="inline">
                     <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause some of our Friends have writ so, is it reasonable that we should all be concluded by them, because some of us have writ so? there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to conclude all are no <hi>Christians,</hi> This is not fair.</hi>
                  </q> So again, <hi>pag.</hi> 75. In <hi>Jer. Ives</hi>'s Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumption of the Answer, he reports <hi>G. White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head</hi> to have said, <q rend="inline">
                     <hi>Must all be concluded to be <hi>No Christians,</hi> because some have written re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to <hi>Christianity?</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Except.</hi> 1.</label> In this Instance I charge the Relation with <hi>Falshood,</hi> for representing <hi>G. Whitehead,</hi> as speaking that which he neither did, nor in Reason can be supposed to speak;
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:204828:12"/> for it makes <hi>G. W. absolutely grant</hi> what he neither did nor could grant, but only <hi>supposed</hi> for Argument sake. That the Design of the Relation was to render him as <hi>granting</hi> that some of our Friends, some of Us, some <hi>Quakers</hi> have written repugnant to <hi>Christia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,</hi> is plain and obvious; and <hi>Jer. Ives</hi> from this forged Concession forthwith infers this Consequence, <q rend="inline">
                     <hi>Doth not this strongly and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently follow, that some <hi>Quakers</hi> have been, or are No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Christians?</hi>
                  </q> But that <hi>G. W.</hi> did not so express himself, not only <hi>cogent Reason evinces,</hi> but even <hi>their own</hi> Relation doth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so evidence, pag. 76. where he thus speaks, <hi>I argued from a particular to a general, and drew a Conclusion from the whole; Supposing</hi> [this is not Granting] <hi>some</hi> Quakers <hi>did speak and write those things that we cannot generally stand by; I have brought them to this, that the</hi> Baptists <hi>themselves would not be so dealt by, though I do not know</hi> (I speak conscientiously) <hi>of any known real</hi> Quaker <hi>among us that has written &amp; laid down that as the</hi> Quakers <hi>Belief, that we cannot stand by; and therefore I am far enough from making any such</hi> Hypothesis, <hi>&amp;c. But it was to awaken them, &amp; bring them to this Consideration, to do as they would be done unto. Suppose these Persons should produce some parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:204828:13"/> things out of some Books that we cannot stand by</hi> (though I know not one) <hi>would these Persons be so dealt with? &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Observe now Reader, I entreat thee, where the <hi>Stress</hi> of my Exception lies: <hi>G. W.</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prest himself by Supposition only <hi>(Suppose any should have written so or so)</hi> and solemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and conscientiously affirmed, that he did <hi>not know of any one</hi> real <hi>Quaker</hi> that had so written, and that therefore he was <hi>far from</hi> making any such <hi>Hypothesis,</hi> from whence might be inferred, that he did <hi>grant</hi> any real <hi>Quaker</hi> had so written; yet their Relation <hi>turns this Supposition into a down-right Conces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion,</hi> and represents G. W. as <hi>plainly and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solutely granting, that some of the</hi> Quakers <hi>had written repugnant to</hi> Christianity. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst this I <hi>except▪</hi> and herein charge the Relation with being <hi>notoriously false;</hi> and whether my Exception be rightly grounded (the Premises considered) I willingly submit to thy Judgment.</p>
               <p>Again▪ It appears, that this Relation of theirs was <hi>not Really and truly taken from the Mouthes of the Disputants</hi> in the time of the Dispute (but rather patcht up since, according as they were able and willing to remember) in that it makes them speak in <hi>other</hi> Terms,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:204828:13"/> then those by which they exprest themselves. For instance:</p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Except.</hi> 2.</label> In pag. 79. <hi>J. Ives</hi> having for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med an Argument, the Relation sayes <hi>Geo. Keith</hi> cryed out, <hi>He denyed both Major and Minor;</hi> whereas it is most notorious that <hi>G. K.</hi> waved those Terms, and instead thereof used the 1st and 2d Proposition, that he might the better accommodate his Speech to the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity of the vulgar Auditors.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Except.</hi> 3.</label> The Relation makes <hi>W. Penn</hi> and <hi>G. Keith</hi> frequently deliver themselves to <hi>J. Ives singly,</hi> in the plural Particle, <hi>You</hi> and <hi>Your;</hi> which is so generally known not to be the <hi>Quakers Dialect,</hi> that this alone were sufficient to evince that <hi>the Relation was writ by rote.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Except.</hi> 4.</label> In page 83. of their Relation, <hi>G. K.</hi> is made to say, <hi>I deny that Mr.</hi> Penn <hi>is no</hi> Christian. This also I refer to the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der's Consideration, whether there be any the least Probability, that <hi>G. K.</hi> who is a <hi>Quaker,</hi> should in a publick Auditory call <hi>William Penn by the Title of Mr. Penn</hi> This plainly enough discovers that the <hi>Penman exercised his Fancy more then his Ears.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If it shall be objected that these are but <hi>trivial</hi> Circumstances, not <hi>material</hi> Passages; I answer, That though they are not material
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:204828:14"/> to evidence the Strength or Weakness of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments on either side; yet they are <hi>material enough</hi> to evince, that the Account it self, which <hi>T. Plant</hi> has publisht of the second Dispute was <hi>not really and truly taken there,</hi> as the Discourse dropt from the Mouthes of the Disputants, but <hi>written since by Rote,</hi> not as it really was, but as he and others thought fit to represent it. And seeing they have so ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parently misreported us in things of <hi>lesser moment,</hi> why should the Reader question <hi>their Propensity to do the like in Matters more substantial?</hi> But this also I subject to the Reader's Censure.</p>
               <p>Again, pag. 72. A Stranger having ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prest his Desire, that our Charge might be read and prosecuted, was thereupon suspect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by one of the <hi>Baptists</hi> to be a <hi>Priest</hi> or a <hi>Romanist</hi> at least; whereof the Stranger com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining, <hi>J. Ives</hi> puts him upon his Purgati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: He answers, <hi>I am no Roman Catholick.</hi> Whereupon <hi>Jeremy</hi> replies, <hi>But are you not a</hi> Hobbist? <hi>for you talk as if you were.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Except.</hi> 5.</label> Here again the Relation <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayes it self,</hi> for thinking it <hi>too bald</hi> for <hi>Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my</hi> to put such a Question upon an already-abused Stranger, without shewing some Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son for it, they add this as the Ground of his Question <hi>[for you talk as if you were]</hi>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:204828:14"/> Now if this was not then spoaken, but since added (as I object) then it follows, that the Relation is not faithful. If they will insist, that it was then spoaken by <hi>J. Ives,</hi> then I desire the Reader to consider from <hi>what part</hi> of this Stranger's <hi>Talk</hi> he had Ground to suggest him an <hi>Hobbist;</hi> which, that the Reader may the better do, I will not think much to setdown the whole of what they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port him to have spoaken, just as I find it in their Relation, which begins thus:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gentlemen, I am neutral, and do speak what is equal: they are willing to prove</hi> T. Hicks <hi>a Forger, and say, it is the first Article agreed to be discoursed this day, therefore it is reasonable they should go on to prove it; for if I am Plantiff, you are to answer my Accusati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> p. 70.</p>
               <p>His next words are these; <hi>Hear the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of the Charge read, that we may under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand them,</hi> p. 71.</p>
               <p>His next words are these; <hi>I am charged, and desire to be heard.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His next words are these; <hi>I am no Roman-Catholick,</hi> that is, <hi>I am not of that Church,</hi> pag. 72.</p>
               <p>This is to a Tittle what they relate him to have said before this second Suggestion of an <hi>Hobbist,</hi> which is grounded <hi>upon his Talk,</hi> from
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:204828:15"/> whence what Ground <hi>J. I.</hi> could have to sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect the Man an <hi>Hobbist</hi> (which in plainer <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish,</hi> is an <hi>Atheist</hi>) I leave to thee (Reader) to consider, while I pursue my present purpose, which is, <hi>to prove the Relation false.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>One of these three Inconveniencies will, I think, inevitably befal the <hi>Baptists</hi> in this case. If they acknowledge, that this Clause was not then spoaken, but since added by them to countenance and <hi>flourish over</hi> the Suggestion, it will follow, <hi>that the Relation is False:</hi> If they will affirm, that it was then spoaken, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as it is there set down, the Danger still will be as great; for, inasmuch as what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever they have related, as spoaken by this Stranger, cannot possibly administer the least Colour or Pretence for such a Suggestion, it must needs be, that either he spake some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing else, which they have <hi>not related, but concealed,</hi> and <hi>then the Relation is False still;</hi> or else, that the Suggestion was <hi>wholely ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less,</hi> and the Reason given for it, <hi>false;</hi> and then <hi>J. Ives</hi> may fall under the Censure of his Brother <hi>Russell,</hi> as his Brother <hi>Russel</hi> did un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his.</p>
               <p>Thus, Reader, I have given thee a few Instances, yet enough (I hope) to satisfie thy Judgment of the <hi>Falshood</hi> and <hi>Partiality</hi> of their Relation. Many other parts of it I can
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:204828:15"/> except against as <hi>false,</hi> upon my own Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; but I would not, <hi>like them,</hi> impose upon thy Belief, and therefore insist on such Particulars, as (even from their own Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) are plainly demonstrable to thy Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing; by which, <hi>as of the Lyon by his Paw,</hi> thou mayest take a measure of the rest.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III. Some Observations on the most Material Pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sages in his Relation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Although, <hi>Reader,</hi> having already enerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the force of the <hi>Relation,</hi> by shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that <hi>it is imperfectly and partially written,</hi> I might well excuse my self from taking any further notice of it; yet a little to manifest the <hi>Weakness</hi> of their <hi>Disputant,</hi> and the <hi>Folly</hi> of their <hi>Relator,</hi> as well as altogether the <hi>Falsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> of the <hi>Relation</hi> it self, I present thee here a few <hi>Observations</hi> on the most material Pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sages in it.</p>
               <p>In the Relation of the first Meeting, <hi>p.</hi> 15. <hi>T. Hicks</hi> is said to answer thus; <q rend="inline">
                     <hi>Concerning that Charge wherein they accuse me for false Reflections upon <hi>Stephen Crisp,</hi> I cannot own this Charge; for I have said no more of him
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:204828:16"/> then what I am able to prove <hi>(viz.)</hi> that he af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed to me, that he knew the Beginning and Date of my Christ &amp;c.</hi>
                  </q> Upon these last words <hi>T. Plant</hi> hath a marginal Note, in these words, <q rend="inline">
                     <hi>This they omitted to read publickly, though all the rest were read at length.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Observ.</label> By this he would seem to hint, that we endeavoured to conceal this Passage from the People. In this he is guilty, first of a <hi>groundless Insinuation;</hi> and next, of a <hi>down-right Falshood,</hi> to colour it. That the Insinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is not only <hi>groundless,</hi> but <hi>ridiculous</hi> also, let it be consider'd, 1st, That it was <hi>we our selves</hi> that inserted this particular in the <hi>Charge.</hi> 2. That we did it <hi>voluntarily</hi> and of Choice, being under no Constraint thereto. 3. That we did it to this End and Purpose, that it might be <hi>publickly</hi> examin'd &amp; discust. With what Shew of Reason can any one then imagine, that we design'd to <hi>conceal</hi> it? That <hi>T. Plant</hi> hath added an <hi>Ʋntruth,</hi> to colour o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver his Insinuation, in saying <hi>All the rest were read at length,</hi> will appear plainly to the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, if he please but to cast an Eye either on our Copy of the Charge as it was that Day read, and since printed with our <hi>Account</hi> of that Meeting, <hi>pag.</hi> 38. or on their own Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>pag.</hi> 6, 7. In both which he may find, that this was not the <hi>only</hi> Passage in the <hi>Charg,</hi> that was abbreviated; but that <hi>his several A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buses
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:204828:16"/> of W. Penn</hi> under one Head, and the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions</hi> charg'd upon <hi>T. Hicks</hi> under ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Head, were in like manner abbreviated also; though <hi>T. Plant</hi> hath the <hi>Confidence</hi> to affirm, that <hi>All the rest</hi> were read at length.</p>
               <p>In <hi>pag.</hi> 23. It being objected, that some of the <hi>Quakers</hi> had affirm'd, that <hi>Christ was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver seen with carnal Eyes;</hi> G. Keith answer'd, I distinguish: <hi>Christ, as God, was never seen with carnal Eyes; but as Man, he was.</hi> To this <hi>Jer. Ives</hi> replies, <hi>He was Christ, as he was Man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Observ.</label> Herein <hi>Jeremy</hi> contradicts his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Hicks:</hi> for he sayes positively (<hi>Dial.</hi> 1. pag. 44.) <hi>Not the meer God-head of the Son, nor the meer Manhood; but God and Man uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in one Person, that is the Christ.</hi> See the Difference: <hi>Tho. Hicks</hi> sayes, <hi>He is Christ</hi> (not as he is Man, but) <hi>as he is God and Man, J. Ives</hi> saith, <hi>He was Christ, as he was Man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Pag. 24. <hi>W. Penn</hi> saith, <hi>When our Friend sayes, Christ was never seen with Carnal Eyes, it is meant of the Divine Nature, which is the more excellent and better Part.</hi> To this <hi>Jer. Ives</hi> replyes, <q rend="inline">
                     <hi>By the same Rule, if I should write a Book, and publish to the World, That I had never seen <hi>W. P.</hi> and <hi>G.K.</hi> in all my Life, and they should tell me I lyed, because I saw them at this Meeting; May I not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:204828:17"/> them with this Distinction, as they do me, and say, That <hi>W. P.</hi> and <hi>G. K.</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist of Soul and Body, and because I never saw their Souls, which is the more excellent Part, therefore I never saw them.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Observ.</label> This Comparison is very unsuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and <hi>smells strongly of Socinianism,</hi> as tending to prove that <hi>Christ was but a meer Man,</hi> and therefore <hi>as obvious to Sight</hi> as <hi>W. P.</hi> and <hi>G. K.</hi> For he makes <hi>no more</hi> of seeing Christ, then he does of seeing either of these two men: Whereas Christ is called in Scripture, The <hi>Mighty God,</hi> Isa. 9.6. <hi>King of Kings, and Lord of Lords,</hi> Rev. 19.16. <hi>whom no man hath seen,</hi> NOR CAN SEE, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.16.</p>
               <p>Upon this Passage <hi>T. Plant</hi> makes a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal Note in these words; <q rend="inline">
                     <hi>
                        <hi>Note,</hi> That this Opinion of the <hi>Quakers,</hi> that Christ was not seen with Carnal Eyes, is laid down by them in Opposition to the Priests &amp; false Ministers, as they call them</hi>
                  </q> [Do ye <hi>Baptists</hi> then own the Priests to be True Ministers now? Sure I am ye did not use to do so formerly. Or do ye only <hi>fawn</hi> on them, that they may <hi>assist</hi> you in your <hi>War</hi> against us?] <q rend="inline">
                     <hi>But <hi>(sayes he)</hi> if <hi>W. P's</hi> and <hi>G. K</hi>'s Distinction be good, then they make their Friends to fight with the Air: For who doth he oppose? since
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:204828:17"/> never any was so idle us to preach that the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Nature was ever seen with Carnal Eyes: So that either they make their Friends write vainly, or else their Distinction is here im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Observ.</label> Here I observe, that the same time, while the <hi>Baptist's</hi> contend that <hi>Christ was seen with Carnal Eyes;</hi> they also say, that the <hi>Divine Nature was never seen with Carnal Eyes;</hi> thereby <hi>divesting Christ of the Divine Nature,</hi> and representing him no other then <hi>a meer Man.</hi> That thou may'st see, Reader, that this is indeed the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequence of their Assertion, let me cast it into the Form of an Argument thus:
<list type="syllogism">
                     <item>If the Divine Nature was not seen with Carnal Eyes, then the Manhood only was seen with Carnal Eyes:</item>
                     <item>But the Divine Nature was not seen with Carnal Eyes;</item>
                     <item>Therefore the Manhood only was seen with Carnal Eyes.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>I do not see that the Consequence of the first Proposition can be excepted against: The second is their own Assertion, and the Conclusion natural. Let us see what the Issue will be.
<list type="syllogism">
                     <item>If the Manhood only was seen with Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Eyes, and yet Christ was seen with
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:204828:18"/> Carnal Eyes, then the Manhood was only Christ:</item>
                     <item>But the Manhood only was seen with Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Eyes, and yet Christ was seen with Carnal Eyes;</item>
                     <item>Therefore the Manhood only was Christ.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>The Consequence of the first Proposition I take to be undeniable: The second is partly the Consequence of the former Argument, and partly their own Assertion: The Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion fair and genuine. By this, Reader, thou mayst see what this Assertion of theirs, <hi>That Christ was seen with Carnal Eyes,</hi> leads unto and issues in, viz. <hi>The Denyal of his Divinity or God-head,</hi> and making him but <hi>a meer Man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here for an Account of our Carriage that Day, he refers his Reader to a Book, entitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>The</hi> Quakers <hi>Quibbles, publish'd</hi> (he sayes) <hi>by an Ingenuous Indifferent Person.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I will not say much to it, enough having been said already by another. But if thou thy self, Reader, art an Ingenuous or Indifferent Person, this Justice I desire of thee, that thou wilt conclude nothing against us from that Book, till thou hast read our Answer to it, which bears this Title, <hi>The</hi> Quakers <hi>Plainess detect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Fallacy.</hi> Remember that prudent Saying of a Just <hi>Heathen.</hi>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:204828:18"/>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Sen. <hi>in Medea.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Qui statuit aliquid, parte inaudita altera,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Equum licet statuerit, haud aquus fuit.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q> Which may bear this <hi>English.</hi>
                  <q>
                     <l>He that, but one Part heard, shall undertake</l>
                     <l>An hasty Judgment on the whole to make,</l>
                     <l>Although his Judgment should prove true, yet he</l>
                     <l>An Unjust Judge shall still reputed be.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>But I proceed.</p>
               <p>In p. 24. <hi>J. Ives</hi> proposed a Question, <q rend="inline">
                     <hi>Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Human Nature be a Part of the true Christ of God, now in Heaven making Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cession for us?</hi>
                  </q> Upon which <hi>T. Plant</hi> takes an Occasion to abuse us thus:</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="inline">
                     <hi>Here <hi>(sayes he)</hi> they all sate down as men astonisht for a Considerable Time: an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer was called for again and again, but the <hi>Quakers</hi> sate speechless.</hi> So p. 25. <hi>Which was a Wonder to behold Men of their Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to be so gravely mute for so long a time together, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Observ.</label> In this they have <hi>grosly abused us,</hi> and manifestly <hi>discovered their own Weakness;</hi> for here they would insinuate that we were <hi>not able to answer,</hi> but sate down like Men, asto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisht,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:204828:19"/>
                  <hi>speechless</hi> for a considerable Time, <hi>mute</hi> for a long Time, &amp;c. And yet <hi>J. Ives</hi> in his <hi>Questions for the Quakers,</hi> p. 10. tells his Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that <hi>We spake mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>, &amp; spake last.</hi> How well these will hang together let the Reader judge. But besides, the Author of the <hi>Quakers Quib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles,</hi> whom they highly applaud for Ingenuity &amp; Indifferency, tells us upon this very Subject, p. 17. <hi>He believes</hi> W.P. <hi>spake above a Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand Words</hi> (which was far enough from being mute and speechless) and p. 11. he confesses, <hi>We cryed out to be heard.</hi> And not without Cause: For indeed <hi>J. Ives</hi> had cunningly rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed such a Noise and Clamour, that it was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possible for us, while that remained, to be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinctly heard; but so soon as our Importuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty had obtained Silence, we plainly and fully confest to, and acknowledged the Holy Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of Christ.</p>
               <p>After the Relation of the first Meeting is ended, <hi>T. Plant</hi> goes on, to give his <hi>Reader</hi> an Account of some Letters that past between them and us, in Order to a second, Introducto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to which he writes thus, <hi>After this (not hearing from them</hi> (i. e. the <hi>Quakers</hi>) <hi>and considering the Ʋnlikelyhood of ever coming to a right Ʋnderstanding each of other,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Observ.</label> Hence, <hi>Reader,</hi> observe the <hi>hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:204828:19"/> Injustice</hi> of these Men towards us. <hi>Tho. Hicks</hi> had long before, in three Books suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessively charged us, That <hi>We render the Holy Scriptures to be of no more Autority then the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of</hi> Esop: That <hi>the Blood of Christ in our E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steem, is worse then the Blood of a common Thief:</hi> That <hi>the</hi> Quakers <hi>have discovered themselves to be no other but the Spawn of that wicked Brood the</hi> Ranters, <hi>having licked up their Vomit:</hi> That <hi>the</hi> Quakers <hi>owning Jesus Christ is indeed no other then a meer Mystical Romance:</hi> That <hi>the Tendency of all the</hi> Quakers <hi>Reasoning about Instituted Religion, is to debauch Mankind:</hi> That <hi>our Principles improved, are destructive to all human Society:</hi> That <hi>we are Cheats, Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postors, Lyar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, influenced by the Devil, the Devils Slaves, inspired by that grand Impostor, the Devil, implacable Enemies to the</hi> Christian <hi>Religion, as vile Impostors as ever were,</hi> and much more of the same Nature. The <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tists</hi> being appealed to for <hi>Justice</hi> herein, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit him. Being drawn <hi>(with much ado)</hi> to debate it in a publick Assembly, <hi>T. Hicks</hi> there also sayes, I do not yet see Reason to <hi>abate them one Word:</hi> And both he and <hi>J. Ives</hi> there affirm, That <hi>the</hi> Quakers <hi>are no</hi> Christians. And yet after all this they are so blind as to confess, <hi>They are not yet come to a Right Ʋnderstand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of us.</hi> Had they not a right Understand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:204828:20"/> of us, and yet would at a Venture thus represent us! <hi>O dishonest and malicious Minds!</hi> And indeed that this was their Design <hi>(viz.)</hi> to traduce, reproach, calumniate us at any <hi>rate how false soever</hi> (like those of old com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained of by the Prophet, <hi>Report,</hi> say they, <hi>and we will Report,</hi> Jer. 20.10.) take one In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance more out of this Book of their own, <hi>pag.</hi> 64. where at the last Meeting, which was on the 16th of <hi>October</hi> past, <hi>J. Ives</hi> confesseth <hi>he had not read</hi> T. Hicks<hi>'s Books, nor</hi> W. Penn's, <hi>until the Night before,</hi> which was the 15th; and yet the same <hi>Jeremy</hi> appear'd publickly in Defence of <hi>T. Hicks,</hi> whom we had charg'd with <hi>Forgeries</hi>) and to prove us <hi>No Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> on the 9th of <hi>October,</hi> which was about a Week before: So that <hi>he first charg'd us to be</hi> No Christians, <hi>and then a Week after read our Books, to see whether we were so, or no.</hi> By these Instances, <hi>Reader,</hi> thou may'st judge, how <hi>Honestly</hi> we have been dealt with by them.</p>
               <p>In their Letter of <hi>October</hi> 21. pag. 26. They write thus, <hi>But forasmuch that in publick Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, Tumults and Noises happen,</hi> AND WE KNOW NOT WHERE TO LAY THE BLAME, &amp;c. yet in their very next Letter, dated <hi>October</hi> 14. pag. 30. they write thus, <hi>All which is drown'd and lost in the Acclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:204828:20"/> and Exclamations of such a populous &amp; nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous Assembly, as by the late Instance of</hi> Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bican <hi>too much appears,</hi> ESPECIALLY ON YOUR PART TOO APPARENTLY.</p>
               <p>And pag. 36. they write thus, <hi>Again they</hi> (meaning the <hi>Quakers</hi>) <hi>are troubled that the Rudeness of the</hi> Barbican <hi>Meeting should be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flected on them:</hi> DID THEY NOT DE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SERVE IT? <hi>Yea, was it not</hi> APPARENT <hi>to every impartial Person there present?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Observe, <hi>Reader,</hi> how they can <hi>Say and Ʋn-say, Blow Hot and Cold with the same Breath:</hi> Yer now <hi>they knew not where to lay the Blame;</hi> Now all on a suddain, 'tis <hi>We deserve it,</hi> 'twas <hi>too apparently on our part,</hi> yea <hi>'twas apparent to every impartial Person present.</hi> How chance then it was <hi>not apparent</hi> to those <hi>five</hi> wise Men that subscribed that Letter, wherein they say, <hi>The knew not where to lay it?</hi> Was it, because <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ey were Partial? Thou seest, <hi>Reader,</hi> ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> these Men <hi>play fast and loose.</hi> Surely, if they regarded to speak the plain and naked Truth of things, they could not thus <hi>thwart and contradict themselves;</hi> but having <hi>devoted</hi> themselves, to <hi>Defame us</hi> Right or Wrong, they are <hi>justly</hi> left to <hi>discover their own Folly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Their Propositions to avoid a Publick Mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, were dated <hi>Octob.</hi> 12. We return'd them
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:204828:21"/> an Answer dated the 13th. On the 14th they write us another, wherein they complain thus, <hi>Instead of answering our Proposals, you send to us, without taking the</hi> LEAST NOTICE <hi>of ours; but</hi> WHOLELY WAVING <hi>so much as the</hi> MENTION <hi>of them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Observ.</label> To manifest the Falsness of this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection, I will desire the Reader but to cast his Eye on the very first Period of our Letter, as they have printed it, <hi>p.</hi> 28. which begins thus,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>We</hi> RECEIV'D <hi>your</hi> PROPOSALS dated <hi>Octob.</hi> 12. <hi>which admit of so much Delay, for the Prosecution of our Charges against</hi> T. Hicks, <hi>as we cannot yield unto, nor will our Occasions permit such a tedious Attendence; as also we do not perceive, that you intend Justice against</hi> Th. Hicks <hi>in your new Propositions</hi> (a private Mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting not being answerable to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>s publick Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries) <hi>however, there remains a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>y for it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Judge now, Reader, whether this was <hi>not taking the least notice of their Proposals,</hi> but <hi>wholy waving so much as the mention of them;</hi> whenas, in this very Letter, we tell them, <hi>we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived their Proposals,</hi> and except against them in general, as <hi>too dilatory;</hi> in particular, as offering a <hi>private</hi> Meeting instead of a <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick;</hi> and yet they have the Confidence here to tell us, that <hi>we took not the least Notice of them,</hi> but <hi>wholely waved so much as the men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:204828:21"/> of them.</hi> Who could have believed these men would have dealt so <hi>dishonestly,</hi> if they had not given it us under their own hands? (for the Letter is subscribed by <hi>Tho. Paul, Tho. Plant, Jer. Ives, Jos. Morton</hi>) And <hi>Jer. Ives,</hi> with no less Confidence, then if he had really believed it to be true, <hi>affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the same thing</hi> over and over at the last Meeting (viz.) That <hi>we took No Notice of their Proposals, nor of their Letter wherein the Proposals were,</hi> pag. 41, 42. What men, I say, not of Worthy Minds <hi>(for that I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver expected in them)</hi> but of <hi>Common Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesty</hi> among men, would deal thus basely with their Adversaries! Surely, one would think, that <hi>an Habit of speaking Falsly, had made them forget at all to speak True.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Their Animadversions upon our Letter de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve not much Consideration; therefore I will but cursorily run over them, and here and there touch some particular Passages.</p>
               <p>They say, p. 35. <hi>Our Denying the Lord's Christ will be proved, when we are free to sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to an Orderly Meeting.</hi> (And this is spoaken in Opposition to a Publick Meeting.)</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Observ.</label> But if Meetings are Disorderly <hi>because</hi> Publick, then <hi>themselves are guilty</hi> of having appointed the <hi>first</hi> Disorderly Mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:204828:22"/> at <hi>Barbican:</hi> They did not think that Meeting at all <hi>too publick</hi> or disorderly, to <hi>Traduce, Slander</hi> and <hi>Rail</hi> against us in; but when we <hi>call them to an Account</hi> for their <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieties,</hi> O then, <hi>Let that be private,</hi> cry they; for Publick Meetings are Disorderly.</p>
               <p>But that they might cast the Rudeness of the <hi>Barbican.</hi> Meeting upon the <hi>Quakers,</hi> they say, pag. 36. <hi>Was there not a deep Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence when any of them spake; whereas on the other side, if any were speaking, what a Noise and Clamour was there?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Observ.</label> Though this Insinuation be <hi>malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously designed,</hi> yet it is too <hi>weakly</hi> and <hi>shallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> laid to do us any harm; for it is observable, that for all the <hi>deep Silence</hi> when the <hi>Quakers</hi> spake, <hi>Tho. Plant</hi>'s Relation of that Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing gives but <hi>about Sixteen Lines in all</hi> of what all the <hi>Quakers</hi> said there; and yet, notwithstanding the <hi>Noise and Clamour,</hi> that he sayes, was made when any of the <hi>Baptists</hi> spoak, he gives us <hi>no less then Seven Pages</hi> of one entire continued Discourse made by <hi>Tho. Hicks</hi> (who yet they say, had but a Weak Voice) Surely, one would think their No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary had <hi>long Ears,</hi> which he prickt up at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentively when <hi>T. Hicks</hi> spake (else could it hardly have been possible, from <hi>a Low Voice,</hi>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:204828:22"/> so punctually to have pen'd so <hi>large a Sermon</hi> amidst so <hi>great Rudeness, Tumults, Noises, Clamours, Acclamations</hi> and <hi>Exclamations,</hi> as <hi>T. Plant</hi> sayes, were there made) but that he stopt his Ears, or was fallen into a <hi>deep Sleep,</hi> when any of the <hi>Quakers</hi> spake, else questi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onless he might have pickt up <hi>above Sixteen Lines</hi> in so <hi>deep a Silence,</hi> as is said to attend their Speech.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tho. Plant</hi> goes on, pag. 35. <hi>Further, they are pleased to say, They were Treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rously Betrayed into a Multitude, without equal Place. If</hi> (sayes he) <hi>by Them, they mean them that subscribed the Letter now under Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sideration, then what they say, is manifestly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>true, forasmuch as they had the best Place in that Meeting.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Observ.</label> This is <hi>artificially</hi> and <hi>colourably</hi> spoaken, to <hi>beguile</hi> an <hi>unwary</hi> Reader; but it must not pass so. Our Complaint consist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of two parts; one, <hi>That we were betrayed into a Multitude;</hi> the other, That <hi>we had not Equal Place and Fair Treatment</hi> (though this latter part he hath dropt, as being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps conscious to himself, that we were not fairly treated by them) He concludes the <hi>whole untrue,</hi> and grounds his <hi>Conclusion</hi> on such a <hi>Reason,</hi> as, if it self were true, could yet at most <hi>extend but to a part.</hi> This Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clusion
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:204828:23"/> I reject, as <hi>fallacious;</hi> for, supposing <hi>(not granting)</hi> what he sayes to be true, that we had the best Place, yet it will not thence follow, that we were <hi>not betrayed</hi> into a Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, <hi>before</hi> we possest that Place. If there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it appear, that <hi>we were so Betrayed,</hi> then what he is pleased to call manifestly untrue, will (I hope) be granted to be <hi>manifestly true.</hi> That we were indeed so Betrayed, and <hi>that by</hi> Tho. Plant <hi>himself, on whose solemn Word we relyed,</hi> I offer this short Account of that Transaction to the Reader's Consideration.</p>
               <p>A little before the Hour appointed for the Meeting to begin, those Friends of ours, who were more particularly concerned in that Day's Business, were met together at <hi>George Watt</hi>'s House, being as near the Meeting-Place as conveniently they could, and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing that the Throng in the Streets and Alleys was great, it was judged advisable to send some to the <hi>Baptists</hi> (who were also at a Friends House of theirs not far off) to desire them, That <hi>inasmuch as the Meeting-Place was their own, and consequently the Command of the Doors in their Power, we might not be surprized by their sudden opening of the Doors without Warning, and thereby be exposed to the Labour and Difficulty of Pressing through the Croud to the Place which they assigned for us.</hi>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:204828:23"/> Three of our Friends, namely, <hi>William Mead, John Osgood</hi> and <hi>Theophilus Green,</hi> went unto them with this Message, and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered it amongst divers of them: Whereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Thomas Plant himself</hi> returned an Answer to this purpose; <hi>Tell your Friends, I my self will come to them, and will bring them in at the Back-Door of the Meeting-House, and will see them seated in the Gallery that is appointed for them, before the People are let in.</hi> Upon this <hi>Promise of his</hi> we relied, thinking that in a Matter of no greater Moment, <hi>we</hi> might have been <hi>secure</hi> in <hi>Tho. Plant</hi>'s <hi>Word:</hi> But <hi>it proved far otherwise;</hi> for, <hi>before</hi> he gave us Notice, the Doors were <hi>set open,</hi> and the People <hi>let in;</hi> so that when we came there, we found not only the Galleries round about <hi>filled,</hi> but the <hi>Room</hi> it self below so <hi>thronged,</hi> that we had much ado to <hi>press in</hi> so far as the Bottom of those Stairs that led up to the Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery; and the Stairs themselves were so be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>set, that it was not without very great Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty (and some Danger) that we <hi>at length</hi> obtained the Place.</p>
               <p>Judge now (Reader) whether we were not <hi>Betrayed into a Multitude;</hi> and whether <hi>Thomas Plant,</hi> of all men, had any Reason to <hi>quarrel with us,</hi> for modestly and privately
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:204828:24"/> complaining of this <hi>Treachery,</hi> when he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self was the man by whom we were <hi>Betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now as to the second part of our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint, which concerns Equal Place, &amp;c. that is also true: For beside their Gallery (which seem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed much larger then that which was assigned for us) they had a <hi>spacious Pulpit</hi> also (capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of receiving Three of their Speakers at a time) from whence their Voices might much better reach the Auditory, and where they stood <hi>undisturbed</hi> (till their Fear of its falling made them <hi>flye out of it</hi>) and secured from the <hi>Croudings and Pressings</hi> of others: Whereas the Gallery allotted us, was a very Straight and Narrow Place, scarce capable (I judge) of receiving Twenty Persons, though extreamly thronged, and as it were, wedged together.</p>
               <p>Again. pag. 36. <hi>Tho. Plant</hi> goes on thus, <hi>But they adventure unjust too, in declining the Subject to be proved. Herein</hi> (sayes he) <hi>they Err; for whatever of Fault there was of this kind, it most properly reflects on themselves; for we would have kept to it, but they declin'd it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Observ.</label> In this (Reader) <hi>we are greatly abused,</hi> which that I may fully demonstrate, I beg thy Patience, if hereupon I a little <hi>dilate</hi> my Discourse, because the true <hi>opening</hi>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:204828:24"/> and right <hi>stating</hi> of this <hi>Particular</hi> will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce much to the Discovery of their Shuffl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and <hi>unfair Dealing with us,</hi> in the Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of this Controversie; this being indeed the very <hi>Hinge</hi> whereon they play and turn, and whereby they have endeavoured to turn us off, and <hi>divert us from pursuing our Charge of FORGERY against their Brother</hi> Hicks.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tho. Hicks</hi> writ a Book under the Title of <hi>A Dialogue;</hi> in which he represents two Persons discoursing together, to one of which <hi>he gives</hi> the Name <hi>Christian,</hi> to the other the Name <hi>Quaker:</hi> In this Dialogue he sayes, is <hi>faithfully represented some of the Chief and Most Concerning Opinions of the</hi> Quakers; <hi>together with their Method and Manner of Reasoning in Defence thereof:</hi> and this was not said to be <hi>composed</hi> or <hi>written,</hi> but only <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lisht</hi> by <hi>T. H.</hi> By which <hi>Artifice</hi> the <hi>unwary</hi> Reader was to be <hi>beguiled</hi> (and many were) into a Perswasion, that this Dialogue <hi>was</hi> (not a meer Fiction of <hi>T. H</hi>'s own devising, but) <hi>a real and true Discourse, that had actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally passed between two such Persons, in the hearing of</hi> T. H. <hi>and that what they had real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly spoaken he had only published.</hi> And indeed, what Reader, that did not well weigh the <hi>Inconsistency</hi> of the <hi>Answers</hi> to the <hi>Principle</hi>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:204828:25"/> of the <hi>Person,</hi> but might easily have been <hi>deceived</hi> by such a <hi>Stratagem. T. H.</hi> finding that this took with some, shortly after <hi>emits a second</hi> of the same import: Both these were answered by <hi>William Penn,</hi> in a Book called, <hi>Reason against Railing;</hi> and <hi>Thomas Hicks</hi> therein <hi>detected</hi> of <hi>Forgery, Perversion, Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Slandering, &amp;c.</hi> He (as one of those whom the Apostle said, <hi>would wax worse and worse,</hi> 2 Tim. 3.13.) adds to his former Two a Third, wherein he attempts to justifie his former (for <hi>Scelere velandum est scelus,</hi> said the <hi>Tragaedian</hi> of old) This also was answer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>William Penn</hi> in another Book, called, <hi>The Counterfeit Christian Detected;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in T. H's former <hi>Forgeries</hi> and <hi>Perversions</hi> were <hi>fixt</hi> a little <hi>faster</hi> on him, and divers of his <hi>new ones</hi> added: In this Book an <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal</hi> was made to the <hi>Baptists</hi> for <hi>Justice</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst T. H. and it was exprest <hi>particularly</hi> under those <hi>two Heads</hi> of <hi>Forgery</hi> and <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versions;</hi> the words are these, pag. 28. <hi>With you the People called</hi> Anabaptists, <hi>I leave this Section</hi> (which is the Section of Forgery) <hi>Right us, Right your selves; Right our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession of such an Ʋnfair Adversary, and your selves of so scandalous an Advocate.</hi> Then again, in pag. 40. <hi>Thus have I finished my Observations on his Perversions, leaving them
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:204828:25"/> also with the People called</hi> Anabaptists, <hi>upon whom I cannot chuse but frequently call for Justice against this their Ʋnjust Member.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Upon this <hi>Appeal,</hi> the Baptists <hi>take an Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity</hi> to call <hi>T. Hicks</hi> to an Account (as they say) <hi>those Friends of ours who were most immediately concern'd being absent.</hi> They pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure a Meeting <hi>as publick as they could:</hi> There <hi>T. Hicks</hi> is set forth to <hi>Traduce, Reproach</hi> and <hi>Misrepresent us</hi> to the People, which done the <hi>Baptists acquit</hi> him. We complain of this <hi>unfair</hi> and <hi>unjust Proceeding,</hi> demand a <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Meeting,</hi> where <hi>we also may be present</hi> to exhibit and make good <hi>our Charge of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery, &amp;c.</hi> against <hi>T. Hicks.</hi> We are <hi>long de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay'd;</hi> at length <hi>with Difficulty</hi> prevail. We meet; our <hi>Charge</hi> is read, the first <hi>Article</hi> whereof is this, <hi>A Dialogue between a Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an and a Quaker</hi> [yet made by <hi>T. Hicks</hi>] viz. <hi>wherein</hi> (saith he) <hi>is faithfully represented some of the chief and most concerning Opinions of the</hi> Quakers, <hi>together with their Method and Manner of Reasoning in Defence thereof; publisht for common Benefit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this Article we <hi>charge</hi> Tho. Hicks <hi>with Forgery:</hi> 1. <hi>In calling that a Dialogue,</hi> which is <hi>not a real Dialogue,</hi> but a Fiction of his own devising 2. <hi>In calling that a</hi> Quaker, <hi>which is not a</hi> Quaker. 3. <hi>In calling that a</hi> Christian,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:204828:26"/>
                  <hi>which is not a</hi> Christian. 4. <hi>In affirming that some of the chief and most concerning Opinions of the</hi> Quakers, <hi>together with their Method and Manner of Reasoning in Defence thereof is, faihfully represented, whenas they are most falsly and abusively represented.</hi> This <hi>pinches</hi> them hard, <hi>perplexes</hi> them much, and they must seek about for some <hi>Meuse to escape through,</hi> else here they are sure to <hi>be caught;</hi> for all the <hi>Art and Strength</hi> they have, can <hi>never defend</hi> this Position. First then they <hi>triffle a while</hi> about the <hi>Nature</hi> of a <hi>Dialogue;</hi> but finding <hi>no Safety</hi> for them there, they betake themselves to <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Refuge:</hi> For, sayes <hi>T. Hicks</hi> in his long Answer, <hi>p.</hi> 18. <hi>If it be, that I have opposed the</hi> Christian <hi>to the</hi> Quaker, <hi>&amp;c. I</hi> SUPPOSE <hi>'tis this they account most Criminal.</hi> Well, but admit <hi>T. Hicks</hi> had <hi>forgot the Maxim,</hi> That <hi>Supposition proves nothing;</hi> yet, what Reason can be offer'd why he should <hi>insist on this Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position</hi> (much less, why we should be <hi>concluded</hi> by it) when we plainly tell him, <hi>he is under a Mistake,</hi> and <hi>his Supposition is false:</hi> for though his naming a <hi>Quaker</hi> in Opposition to a <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian,</hi> be a <hi>sufficient Indication of his malicious Mind;</hi> yet we tell him, we do not account that <hi>his greatest Crime,</hi> inasmuch as we know, that neither the <hi>Christian</hi> nor the <hi>Quaker</hi> whom he hath oppos'd, are <hi>Realities,</hi> but <hi>Phantasms of his
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:204828:26"/> own Imagination.</hi> But this we tell him, is that which we account <hi>most Criminal,</hi> viz. his <hi>Forgeries, Perversions, Lyes, Slanders,</hi> &amp;c. by which he hath <hi>abused,</hi> and most <hi>dishonestly mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>represented our Faith and Principles</hi> to the World.</p>
               <p>But say they, <hi>This Opposing the</hi> Christian <hi>to the</hi> Quaker, <hi>is the first Article of your Charge.</hi> So saith <hi>J. Ives</hi> in the Relation of the last Mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>frequently,</hi> and in <hi>pag.</hi> 49. <hi>especially,</hi> where <hi>T. Plant</hi> also asserts the same, and takes upon him thus to prove it; <hi>This</hi> (saith he) <hi>being the first Article of his Charge, for is not this the first Article of his Charge,</hi> &amp;c? <hi>Was not this</hi> (by the way) <hi>learnedly argued?</hi> However, it was <hi>as learnedly answer'd;</hi> for he makes the People cry, <hi>Yes, Yes:</hi> not considering the Perplexity he puts his Reader into, to bethink, <hi>how the People should come to know it,</hi> whenas <hi>the</hi> Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tists <hi>would not suffer it to be read,</hi> as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves confess, <hi>pag.</hi> 62, 71.</p>
               <p>But <hi>we deny that this is the first Article of the Charge.</hi> Who now, judicious Reader, ought to have the <hi>Examination,</hi> the <hi>Expla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,</hi> the <hi>Stating,</hi> the <hi>Opening</hi> of our <hi>Charge, we that made it,</hi> or he and they <hi>against whom it was made?</hi> One would think, in Reason they might give us Leave <hi>to be so far Masters of our own Charge,</hi> as to <hi>insist on what part of it we please,</hi> &amp; to lay the Stress <hi>where we see good.</hi>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:204828:27"/> But, <hi>if they will not be</hi> (as indeed we seldom find they are) <hi>ruled by Reason,</hi> let us yet see <hi>if they will stand to their own Agreement,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as they themselves have set it down, <hi>pag.</hi> 11. of their Relation. In the second Proviso it is thus exprest, <hi>That upon</hi> OUR <hi>Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of each Particular</hi> T. Hicks <hi>be permitted to give his direct Answer, &amp;c.</hi> This they acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge they consented to, <hi>pag.</hi> 13. Judge now, indifferent Reader, whether <hi>by their own A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement</hi> (as well as in Reason &amp; Justice) it did not <hi>belong to us to determine</hi> what the first Article of the Charge was, and where the Stress of it should ly.</p>
               <p>Thus far, <hi>Reader,</hi> I have ravelled back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, to help thee to a right Understanding what was the <hi>Ground</hi> and <hi>Occasion</hi> of our <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealing</hi> to the <hi>Baptists</hi> for <hi>Justice,</hi> what the <hi>prime Intention</hi> (at least on our parts) of those publick <hi>Meetings</hi> between them and us, and what was indeed and in Truth <hi>the propper Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject</hi> to have been there <hi>debated</hi> and <hi>discust,</hi> viz. The <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Forgery, Lying</hi> and <hi>false Quotations</hi> they themselvs in <hi>pag 4</hi> of <hi>T. Plant</hi>'s Re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lation do acknowledge to be that which be complan'd of, that which we appeal'd to the <hi>Baptists</hi> about, and that which they appointed their Meeting to hear and examine.</note>
                  <hi>Forgeries, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versions, Lyes, Slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, &amp;c.</hi> which had been <hi>written and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lisht by</hi> T. Hicks to <hi>defame our Principles,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:204828:27"/> Practices and Persons.</hi> Now, that thou may'st be fully satisfied that it was <hi>They</hi> declined this Subject, not We, I refer thee to their own Relation, <hi>pag.</hi> 49, 56, 60. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly prove it against them; but especially those words of <hi>J. Ives</hi> in the Postscript, p. 110. <hi>It is observable</hi> (saith he) <hi>that most of the Time spent in the two Dayes Conference was, to prevail upon them to hear our Arguments, to prove, they were no</hi> Christians <hi>&amp; that their Ministers were Cheats and Impostors</hi> (which was not the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to be proved) This is so <hi>clear</hi> an Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence <hi>against them,</hi> and <hi>for us,</hi> that we could not have wisht a <hi>clearer,</hi> to manifest how <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dustriously</hi> they <hi>declined</hi> the Subject, how <hi>close<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> we <hi>adher'd</hi> to it, and how <hi>hardly</hi> we were <hi>drawn</hi> from it.</p>
               <p>I should now have done with this Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, but for a Passage or two relating to it, which I am not willing wholely to pretermit, nor can so properly speak to in any other place. The <hi>first</hi> is in <hi>p.</hi> 70. of their Relation, where <hi>T. Plant</hi> doth with so <hi>high a Confidence,</hi> maintain a <hi>manifest Falshood,</hi> that it makes me fear, the man <hi>(as well as his Cause)</hi> is grown <hi>Desperate.</hi> The Occasion of his Speech was this, <hi>W. Penn prest hard</hi> to come to the <hi>Proof</hi> of our <hi>Charge</hi> of <hi>Forgery;</hi> whereupon <hi>T. Plant</hi> answer'd him thus, <hi>Do not thus abuse the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:204828:28"/> Auditory; for I will shew you here out of your own Book, that the first Complaint against</hi> T. Hicks <hi>is for this thing,</hi> viz. <hi>for writing a Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue, and opposing the</hi> Quaker <hi>to a</hi> Christian, <hi>and therefore do not study Evasions; it is not only, because under the Dialogue is couched Forgery</hi> (Oh! Is there so? how then dare ye <hi>protect, him in it?</hi> Why study ye these Shifts &amp; Evasions to <hi>shelter</hi> him from a <hi>just</hi> Stroke?) <hi>but also, because he opposeth a</hi> Christian <hi>to a</hi> Quaker, <hi>and therefore you call it one of his scurrilous Invectives, that</hi> T. Hicks <hi>should be the Man of all other, that should take upon him to un</hi>-Christian <hi>you, who is not only (as you say) Ʋnjust in doing so, but excessively Imbitter'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst you, and that leads the Ran of the Charge</hi> (viz.) <hi>for writing a Dialogue between a</hi> Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an <hi>and a</hi> Quaker, <hi>and your great Complaint a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst</hi> T. Hicks <hi>is, for that he opposeth a</hi> Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an <hi>to a</hi> Quaker. <hi>This is the first, both in your Book, and the Charge exhibited against him, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now, <hi>Reader,</hi> I desire thee to observe, that <hi>T. P.</hi> doth here <hi>positively</hi> affirm, that T.H's <hi>Opposing the</hi> Quaker <hi>to the</hi> Christian, <hi>is the first Complaint in</hi> W. Penn's <hi>Book against</hi> T. Hicks. That this is most notoriously false, I refer thee, <hi>Reader,</hi> to that very Book of <hi>W. Penn</hi>'s, call'd, <hi>Reason against Railing,</hi> where in <hi>pag.</hi> 170.
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:204828:28"/> thou shalt find those words which <hi>T. Plant</hi> hath refer'd to, viz. <hi>Scurrilous Invectives, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessively imbitter'd, &amp;c.</hi> (though <hi>he hath basely misreported them</hi> to serve his Design) and then turn back to <hi>p.</hi> 143. thou shalt find <hi>T. Hicks</hi>'s <hi>Perversions complain'd of.</hi> Then <hi>p.</hi> 154. <hi>A Collection of his great Lyes.</hi> And in <hi>p.</hi> 158. <hi>His Forgeries detected.</hi> So that <hi>the Complaint against</hi> T. Hicks<hi>'s Perversions is no less then</hi> 27 pages <hi>before those scurrilous Invectives men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd by</hi> T. Plant, <hi>where</hi> he sayes, <hi>the</hi> Quaker <hi>is opposed to the</hi> Christian; and yet the man is <hi>so past all Shame,</hi> as to <hi>affirm</hi> (and that too pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly in Print) <hi>that this Opposing the</hi> Quaker <hi>to the</hi> Christian <hi>is the first Complaint in the Book.</hi> Oh! what is not that Man lyable to, who hath prostituted his Conscience and Understanding to his Interest.</p>
               <p>The next thing, <hi>Reader,</hi> that I would brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly touch is this, The <hi>Appeal</hi> made to them, <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated only to matter of Fact.</hi> This <hi>they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves confess</hi> in their Letter to <hi>J. Osgood,</hi> dated 23. <hi>Aug.</hi> 174. and printed in a Book of theirs, call'd, <hi>The Quakers Appeal answer'd,</hi> Epist. <hi>pag.</hi> 7. Their words are these: <hi>How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, since the Matter depending before us, is</hi> ONLY <hi>matter of Fact, and</hi> NOT <hi>of Dispute, &amp;c.</hi> This I hope, is <hi>plain enough.</hi> But when, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our meeting them at <hi>Barbican,</hi> they found
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:204828:29"/> themselves <hi>unable to defend matter af Fact,</hi> (though before they had publickly <hi>approv'd it,</hi> and <hi>justified</hi> T. Hicks <hi>therein,</hi> which they not only tell the World in the <hi>Epistle</hi> before mention'd, but also confess as much in a <hi>Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> prefixt to <hi>T. Plant</hi>'s Relation, <hi>pag.</hi> 4. where they say, <hi>We are fully satisfied, that in all those</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">This leaves room enough to count all his other <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geries</hi> and Wrongs (couch'd under the <hi>Dialogue</hi>) <hi>Imma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial</hi> or small things.</note>
                  <hi>material things then insisted upon,</hi> T. H. <hi>has done them no Wrong:</hi> then I say, in their <hi>Letter</hi> of the 14th <hi>Octob.</hi> in Answer to ours concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning another <hi>Meeting,</hi> they express them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves thus, <hi>p.</hi> 29. <hi>We gave you a sufficient Proof, and are ready to evidence it to all men, of our Forwardness to proceed in the full Examination and Tryal of whatsoever you have charg'd on</hi> T. H. <hi>about the matter contain'd in his</hi> Dialogues; <hi>and there withal an exact Tryal &amp; Disquisition of your Tenets, whether consistent with the true</hi> Christian <hi>Religion, or not.</hi> I might very well ask them, <hi>By what Authority they would take this upon them?</hi> and <hi>why we may not,</hi> with as good Reason, <hi>examine and try theirs?</hi> But my Aim is more particularly here to shew, That finding <hi>themselvs pincht,</hi> and <hi>hard be set</hi> to <hi>defend</hi> T. H. (and themselves as his Abettors) <hi>in matter of Fact</hi> (which themselves confess,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:204828:29"/> was the <hi>ONLY</hi> thing depending before them) they designedly and <hi>craftily</hi> interweave and <hi>twist in</hi> Matters of <hi>Dispute</hi> (which they also confess, did <hi>NOT</hi> depend before them) that thereby, if it were possible, they might <hi>twist themselves out of those Perplexities,</hi> wherein they found themselves <hi>entangled,</hi> about mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Fact.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I come now to make some few <hi>Observati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> on their <hi>Relation</hi> of the 2d <hi>Meeting,</hi> wherein though I find <hi>many</hi> things <hi>false,</hi> and <hi>many</hi> things <hi>frivolous;</hi> yet I think it not worth either my own or my Reader's While, to take notice of every <hi>Impertinency</hi> and <hi>triffling Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit,</hi> wherewith they have endeavour'd <hi>to varnish over their Relation:</hi> Some few Pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sages however, of those that seem <hi>most mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial,</hi> I will give the Reader a short view of, <hi>by which he may take a measure of the rest.</hi> And I will begin with <hi>J. Ives</hi>'s Definition of a <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian, pag</hi> 58. His words are these:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>All men that seriously believe in the Lord</hi> Christ, <hi>that was crucified for the Sins of men, and is now ascended into Glory; They that believe this, and conform to his Laws, where ever they live; we say, they are good</hi> Christians, <hi>whatsoever Names or Appellations are given to them in this unhappy Age we live in.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:204828:30"/>
               <p>
                  <label>Observ.</label> This Definition of a <hi>Christian</hi> hath two parts: The one contains <hi>certain Articles to be believ'd;</hi> the other, <hi>A Conformity to</hi> Christ's <hi>Laws.</hi> By the first, <hi>The</hi> Pope <hi>may be as good a</hi> Christian <hi>as</hi> Jeremy <hi>himself,</hi> for ought I see; for <hi>he believes as much</hi> concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Lord Christ, <hi>as</hi> Jeremy <hi>here expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth:</hi> And if by the second, viz. <hi>Conformity to</hi> Christ's <hi>Laws,</hi> he respect the <hi>Manner</hi> of Conforming, as well as the <hi>Matter</hi> to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd to, then <hi>Jeremy</hi> plainly <hi>equivocats,</hi> while he seems to <hi>admit others</hi> to be <hi>Christians</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides the <hi>Anabaptists;</hi> for no other People agree with them in the Manner of Conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, <hi>nor they indeed one with another:</hi> So that then, not only <hi>all others are excluded</hi> from any Share in <hi>Christianity</hi> but even <hi>themselves too.</hi> But if on the other hand he respect the <hi>Matter</hi> conform'd to, and not the <hi>Manner</hi> of Conforming, the <hi>Papists</hi> then will be <hi>his good Christians</hi> still; sith they omit nothing which even he accounts Duty, but perform it in a different Mode.</p>
               <p>He goes on, <hi>p.</hi> 61. thus: <hi>If</hi> T. Hicks <hi>or I can prove, that you are no</hi> Christians,—<hi>then is there very good Reason to believe that your Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessing Religion and</hi> Christianity, <hi>and owning the Scriptures, is all but out of sinister Ends, and all your Sufferings are idle and vain; and
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:204828:30"/> this may be the Reason, why you deny a future State; for all these are the Consequences of this antecedent Proposition, that you are no</hi> Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Observ.</label> Two things I observe here: <hi>A foul Insinuation, and a false Conclusion.</hi> The In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sinuation is, <hi>That we deny a future State. This,</hi> Jeremy, <hi>I charge upon thee as a notorious Falshood and malicious Slander; and I put thee upon the Proof thereof,</hi> acquit thy self as thou canst.</p>
               <p>The Conclusion is, That, <hi>If</hi> T. Hicks <hi>or</hi> J. Ives <hi>can prove, that we are no</hi> Christians, <hi>then there is</hi> very good Reason <hi>to believe that our professing Religion and</hi> Christianity, <hi>and own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Scriptures,</hi> is all but out of sinister Ends, &amp;c. <hi>This is false Logick, Jeremy!</hi> Thy Conclusion is <hi>Inconclusive;</hi> thy Conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, a <hi>Non sequitur.</hi> If it were <hi>possible</hi> for T.H. or thee, to prove us no <hi>Christians</hi> (which all the Subtilty of the Serpent <hi>can never do</hi>) yet would it <hi>not</hi> thence follow, <hi>That our</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessing Religion and <hi>Christianity,</hi> and owning the Scriptures, <hi>is all but out of sinister Ends.</hi> There is no <hi>Good Reason,</hi> much less <hi>Charity,</hi> so to believe. How many at this Day do <hi>zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lously</hi> profess Religion and <hi>Christianity,</hi> and own the Scriptures, and that too <hi>without any sinister Ends,</hi> who yet <hi>(alas!)</hi> are far enough
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:204828:31"/> from being <hi>true Christians!</hi> What <hi>sinister Ends</hi> had those ignorant <hi>Athenians,</hi> who wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipped the <hi>Ʋnknown God,</hi> yet were no <hi>true Worshippers?</hi> But if all these be the <hi>Conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences</hi> of this <hi>Antecedent</hi> (as thou say'st) then surely thy <hi>Brother</hi> Hicks <hi>hath set the Cart before the Horse</hi> (as the Proverb is) for he makes that the <hi>Antecedent,</hi> which thou makest the <hi>Consequence;</hi> and that the <hi>Conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent,</hi> which thou makest the <hi>Antecedent.</hi> I hope you'l see that one of you <hi>at least,</hi> is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>side the Mark <hi>(though I see you are both)</hi> and endeavour to <hi>understand your selves,</hi> before you fall upon others.</p>
               <p>Had <hi>Jeremy</hi> lookt but a few Lines lower, he might have seen himself confuting an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, <hi>as like this as may be.</hi> They make <hi>W. P</hi> to say, <hi>I will prove the Book fictitious, and if I do so, then you are no</hi> Christians; <hi>and conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, We are</hi> Christians. <hi>Jeremy</hi> strait re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies, <hi>That's false Logick; for that Book may be fictitious, and yet you may be no</hi> Christians <hi>for all that.</hi> 'Tis false Logick indeed (<hi>and a false Relation too;</hi> for <hi>W. Penn</hi> never so ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gued) but yet it is <hi>as good Logick</hi> as that which <hi>Jeremy</hi> offer'd but now. Would one not wonder his Wits should be so quick and acute all on a sudden, which were so obtuse and dull but just before!</p>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:204828:31"/>
               <p>In p. 88. <hi>T. Plant</hi> inserts a Marginal Note, wherein his Ignorance is worth our noting. <hi>Mark Reader,</hi> sayes he, <hi>here</hi> G. K. <hi>gives away the Cause; for he saith,</hi> W. P. <hi>doth not impose it upon others, nor hath a Call from the Lord to impose it upon others, or require others to believe that he is a</hi> Christian, <hi>and hath immediate In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spiration,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Surely</hi> (adds he) <hi>if this be true, it is no Crime for Mr.</hi> Ives <hi>to say, he is no</hi> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Observ.</label> It seems then (in <hi>T. Plant</hi>'s Sense) if a Man <hi>profess himself a Christian,</hi> and doth <hi>not impose the Belief thereof</hi> upon others, nor hath <hi>a Call from the Lord to require others to believe</hi> that he is a <hi>Christian, he gives away his Cause,</hi> and it is <hi>no Crime to say he is no</hi> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian: What thinkst thou, Reader, <hi>is not this fine arguing?</hi> May I take the Liberty to form such an Argument as this of <hi>T. Plant</hi> against <hi>T. Plant</hi> himself, after this Manner? <hi>If</hi> T. Plant <hi>doth not impose upon others, nor hath a Command from the Lord to require others to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that he is a</hi> Christian, <hi>then it is no Crime for me to say, that</hi> T. Plant <hi>is no</hi> Christian: <hi>But</hi> T. Plant <hi>doth not impose upon others, nor hath a Command from the Lord to require others to believe that he is a</hi> Christian; <hi>Therefore it is no Crime for me to say that</hi> T. Plant <hi>is no</hi> Christian. How will T. Plant <hi>relish</hi> this? will
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:204828:32"/> he sit down now <hi>contentedly</hi> under his own Consequence? If not, let him thank him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self for giving the Occasion for it, and learn to deal <hi>more discreetly and honestly</hi> with his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versaries hereafter.</p>
               <p>But he goes on; <hi>And may not such Men be rejected as idle Impostors, out of their own Mouths? For</hi> (I desire thee Reader, to mark his Argument well) <hi>if he hath no Call from the Lord, to require Men to believe he is a</hi> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian, <hi>as</hi> G. K. <hi>saith; then surely he hath no Call from the Lord to require Men to believe he is a Minister of Christ: But</hi> G. K. <hi>saith,</hi> W. P. <hi>hath no Call from the Lord to require Men to believe he is a</hi> Christian; Ergo, <hi>it followeth he hath no Call from the Lord to require any to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve he is a Minister, and therefore without Sin may be rejected as an idle Impostor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Obs.</label> Here is Ergo <hi>upon</hi> Ergo, Consequence <hi>upon</hi> Consequence, Conclusion <hi>upon</hi> Conclusion <hi>(false Heraldry)</hi> Surely, <hi>this Logick is worth looking into.</hi> Ergo, <hi>it follows he hath no Call from the Lord, to require any to believe he is a Minister</hi> (what then!) <hi>And therefore</hi> [that is, because he hath no Call from the Lord to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire any to believe he is a Minister; <hi>There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore] without Sin he may be rejected as an idle Impostor:</hi> May he so? what sayes <hi>Jeremy</hi> to this? <hi>Is not this false Logick?</hi> (for I doubt
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:204828:32"/>
                  <hi>T. Plant</hi> is so <hi>young a Logician,</hi> that he does not yet <hi>know false from true</hi>) But consider Reader, how nimbly might <hi>T. Plant, at this rate of arguing,</hi> have concluded against any of the Holy Apostles, and have <hi>turn'd them off</hi> as idle Impostors? For which of them all did <hi>take upon him</hi> to <hi>impose</hi> upon his Opposers, or <hi>require such</hi> to believe that he was a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister of Christ; but commended themselves to every Man's Conscience in the Sight of God: But I would not insist too long on this Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness; I will therefore <hi>invert T. Plant</hi>'s Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>upon himself and his own Party,</hi> and that not as my own Judgment, but <hi>Argumentum ad hominem</hi> only, whereby both he and they may see, how <hi>unfairly</hi> they have dealt with us. Take it thus, <hi>If the</hi> Baptist-<hi>Teachers in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral have no Call from the Lord to require others to believe that they are Ministers of Christ, then the</hi> Baptist-<hi>Teachers in general may without Sin be rejected as idle Impostors: But the</hi> Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tist-<hi>Teachers in general have no Call from the Lord to require others to believe that they are Ministers of Christ; Therefore the</hi> Baptist-<hi>Teachers in general may without Sin be reje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted as Idle Impostors.</hi> If this Conclusion seem <hi>over hard</hi> to any of the <hi>Baptists,</hi> let them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider, that the Argument is <hi>not mine,</hi> but <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med for Mischief</hi> by one of their own, and that
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:204828:33"/> I have only <hi>turned back the Point</hi> of it upon themselves: If therefore <hi>they are wounded by their own Weapon,</hi> let them not blame me, but remember that of the Poet.
<q>
                     <l>—<hi>Nec lex est justior ulla,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Quam necis Artifices arte perire suae.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q> Which I will adventure thus to <hi>English:</hi>
                  <q>
                     <l>Nor can a juster Law then this be made,</l>
                     <l>That the Betrayer be himself betray'd;</l>
                     <l>And they that for their Neighbors lay a <hi>snare</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Be taken in the Gin themselves prepare.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>His next Passage affords another Note, and that denotes his <hi>notorious Folly;</hi> It is made upon the Maxim, <hi>De non apparentibus &amp; non existentibus eadem est ratio;</hi> which <hi>G. K.</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed to hold <hi>true in all Cases,</hi> and illustrated his Exception by an Example; whereupon <hi>T. Plant</hi> in his Note sayes, <hi>But it might fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be answered, that the Maxim is true in all Cases in matter of Evidence, about which the Maxim in Law is used; for it doth not appear who had the best, the</hi> French <hi>or the</hi> Dutch; <hi>therefore, it is not evident.</hi> [O profound Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance! as much as if he had said, <hi>It doth not appear, therefore it doth not appear] In like manner</hi> (sayes he) <hi>it appears not that you have a Rule for your Faith and Practice by Inspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, therefore it is not; that is, it is not evidenced.</hi> But prithee Reader, hast thou e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:204828:33"/>
                  <hi>till now</hi> learnt a Distinction between, <hi>it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears not,</hi> &amp; <hi>it is not evidenc'd?</hi> Let us then read him in plain <hi>English</hi> thus, <hi>It appears not that you have a Rule for your Faith and Practice by Inspiration, therefore it is not; that is, it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears not.</hi> It seems then by this he doth not conclude that we have <hi>No Rule,</hi> but only that our Rule doth <hi>not appear;</hi> for when he sayes, it is not, he means only, it is not evidenced; that is, it appears not: So that <hi>this doth not at all oppugn our having a Rule;</hi> though it abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly discovers the Weakness of him that writ it; who <hi>busily</hi> undertaking to explain the Maxim, <hi>that which appears not, is not,</hi> hath at length <hi>most ridiculously</hi> brought it to this issue, that the Meaning of it is, <hi>that which appears not, appears not;</hi> for he makes the Comparison or Parallel to lie <hi>between not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing, and not being evidenced</hi> (which are Terms importing the same thing) whereas in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it ought to lie <hi>between not appearing and not existing or being at all.</hi> And in this sense it is <hi>G. K.</hi> denyes the Maxim to hold <hi>uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versally true:</hi> But enough of this.</p>
               <p>In pag. 92. <hi>J. Ives</hi> asks this Question, <hi>How can any thing be a Rule for a</hi> Christian<hi>'s Faith and Practice, that is evident to no Body but only to him that saith so?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Observ.</label> This Question is grounded upon a
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:204828:34"/>
                  <hi>Mistake</hi> at best, supposing us to affirm, that the Rule of every Individual Person is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to that individual Person only; <hi>which Supposition is false:</hi> for we affirm, That the Rule of our Faith and Practice <hi>is evident to every one,</hi> who hath received and lives by the same holy Faith, which we have received and live by. But the Question rightly stated is this, <hi>Whether every</hi> Christian <hi>is bound (under the Penalty of Forfeiting his</hi> Christianity, <hi>and of being reputed an Heathen, Cheat, Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stor) to give an Evidence (such as no Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stor can imitate) of the Rule of his Faith to those who are Strangers to his Faith, or profest Enemies of it?</hi> This Question reaches the Case; and <hi>I put it closely to</hi> Jer. Ives, Tho. Plant, <hi>and all the rest of them, to answer plainly and fully;</hi> which if they shall do in the <hi>Affirmative,</hi> I expect their <hi>Proof.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After all the <hi>Busle</hi> that <hi>J. Ives</hi> hath made, and all his <hi>loud Clamours</hi> against us, for an Instance, an Instance, an Evidence, an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, whereby we might prove we have a Rule for our Faith and Practice, and <hi>consequently that we are</hi> Christians,</p>
               <p>He now tells us, pag. 101. That <hi>the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign of his Argument was not to prove, that men could not be</hi> Christians <hi>without extraordinary external Evidence.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:204828:34"/>
               <p>
                  <label>Observ.</label> What a <hi>Noise</hi> and <hi>Stir</hi> has he made all this while to prove, that he that <hi>can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not give an Extraordinary External Evidence</hi> (<hi>such</hi> too as no <hi>Impostor</hi> can <hi>imitate</hi>) <hi>is No Christian!</hi> And yet he now plainly grants, that <hi>men may be</hi> Christians <hi>without any Extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary External Evidence.</hi> Thus, <hi>like</hi> A DRUNKEN MAN, <hi>he</hi> REELS <hi>to and fro, in and out, up and down,</hi> one while <hi>affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming one thing,</hi> another while <hi>quite the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And indeed, he that will take the Pains to <hi>trace Jeremy</hi> but through that very Relation, which <hi>themselves</hi> have published, will find him frequently <hi>tripping in his Talk,</hi> his Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course <hi>Contradictory</hi> and <hi>Inconsistent</hi> with it self; his Answers <hi>interfering</hi> and <hi>thwarting one another:</hi> for instance, pag. 49. <hi>Jeremy</hi> sayes, <hi>We say it again, that his first Charge is for writing a Dialogue, and Opposing a</hi> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian <hi>to a</hi> Quaker; <hi>and his first Charge is</hi> NOT <hi>for Forgery:</hi> So pag. 56. <hi>W.P.</hi> sayes <hi>The first Article is for Forgery;</hi> J. Ives sayes, <hi>It is</hi> NOT; <hi>but for writing a Dialogue, and Opposing the</hi> Quaker <hi>to the</hi> Christian: Again, pag. 60. <hi>W. P.</hi> offers <hi>to prove T. Hicks a Forger;</hi> J. Ives answers, <hi>This is</hi> NO PART <hi>of your Charge.</hi> In these three Instances <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remy stoutly</hi> and <hi>boldly</hi> affirms, that <hi>Forgery is</hi>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:204828:35"/> NO PART <hi>of the Charge;</hi> but that the <hi>first Charge is for Opposing a</hi> Quaker <hi>to a</hi> Christian, <hi>and</hi> NOT <hi>for Forgery.</hi> Let us now see what he sayes, pag. 68. his words are these: <hi>I say, this is</hi> ONE PART <hi>or piece of the</hi> FORGERY <hi>that they accuse him of, to sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose and suggest that the</hi> Quakers <hi>are no</hi> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians. Here he has <hi>overturn'd all</hi> he said be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. Now <hi>he confesses</hi> Forgery <hi>is not only in the Charge, but in the first Article too.</hi> Thus, Reader, thou hast heard him <hi>say,</hi> and <hi>say,</hi> and <hi>say again;</hi> and presently after <hi>unsay it all.</hi> Now thou shalt hear him <hi>unsay this too,</hi> and return to his <hi>former Note</hi> again; pag. 71. A Stranger prest that we might have <hi>Liberty to prove our Charge of Forgery; Jer. Ives</hi> takes him up thus, <hi>Forgery,</hi> Sir, <hi>is</hi> NOT <hi>the first Article, as you have heard once and again.</hi> Judge now, Reader, whether this man ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>considers, remembers, understands</hi> or <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gards what he sayes,</hi> who so <hi>palpably and fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently contradicts himself.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nor doth this befal him in the more <hi>loose part</hi> of his Discourse only, but in the <hi>argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentative part</hi> also, which strictly to examine, and particularly to insist on, might of it self fill a larger Treatise then I design this to be; so <hi>false are</hi> Jeremy<hi>'s Arguments, so lame and unconcluding his Conclusions:</hi> One while <hi>he
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:204828:35"/> alters the State of the Question;</hi> another while <hi>he changes the Terms of his Argument:</hi> Sometimes what is <hi>praedicated in his first Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position,</hi> is either <hi>wholely omitted,</hi> or <hi>otherwise repeated in his second.</hi> Of this enough may be seen in pag. 87, 88. where first <hi>the Term praedicated is,</hi> CAN (If <hi>W.P.</hi> hath any Rule, &amp;c. he CAN give some Evidence, &amp;c.) By and by an Occasion is taken to repeat his Argument, and then <hi>from</hi> CAN <hi>'tis drawn to</hi> OUGHT; anon OUGHT <hi>is slipt aside,</hi> and MUST <hi>is thrust in in the room of.</hi> One while the <hi>Proposition</hi> runs thus: If <hi>W. P.</hi> hath any immediate Inspiration, &amp;c. then he hath some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing by which he Can evidence to himself AND to us, &amp;c. and then the <hi>Assumption</hi> is thus; But he hath nothing by which he can evidence this to himself NOR to us. Here instead of the <hi>Copulative</hi> [AND] they have put in the <hi>Disjunctive</hi> [NOR] which not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly marrs the Argument; but renders <hi>Jeremy</hi>'s Business <hi>harder,</hi> which was but <hi>too hard for him before:</hi> for by the <hi>Minor</hi> of this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, he undertakes to prove, <hi>that W. P. hath nothing by which he can evidence to himself that he is no Impostor,</hi> &amp;c. But I doubt in this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, the <hi>Baptists</hi> have <hi>dealt hardly</hi> with their Champion, to <hi>involve him</hi> in such an <hi>inextri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable Difficulty,</hi> after they had spent near <hi>two
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:204828:36"/> Months time,</hi> in <hi>licking</hi> their <hi>Relation</hi> into its present Form. But of this part of it, let this suffice, to give the Reader <hi>a Taste only of</hi> Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remy<hi>'s Arguments;</hi> for I design not here a particular Examination of them, both as that is beside the <hi>Intention</hi> of this Treatise, and as it would be in some respects, a supervacaneous Work; this Manner of Arguing being <hi>some degrees,</hi> beyond the ordinary Understanding of the Vulgar, and to them that are skill'd and exercised in it, the Defects will of themselves be obvious enough, without any Animadver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion: Wherefore leaving this, I proceed to take notice of another of <hi>Tho. Plant</hi>'s Notes, which I find in <hi>p.</hi> 101. thus exprest, <hi>And this Rule ought to be evidenced to be from Heaven Antecedaneously to the Observation of it, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Observ.</label> Herein our Annotator falls short (in my Judgment) of expressing himself <hi>intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligibly:</hi> I enquire therefore of him, <hi>To whom this Rule ought thus to be evidenced; Whether it ought to be evidenced to them that Observe it, or to them that despise or reject it?</hi> If he will say, It ought to be evidenc'd <hi>to them that ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve it</hi> antecedaneously to <hi>their</hi> Observation of it, we herein agree; for we affirm, it is <hi>so</hi> evidenced to us: But if he will say, It ought to be evidenced <hi>to them that despise and reject it,</hi> antecedaneously to <hi>his Observation who
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:204828:36"/> doth receive it, observe it,</hi> and <hi>is to give that Evidence</hi> of it, then he <hi>plunges</hi> himself into as <hi>fond</hi> an <hi>Absurdity,</hi> as he could easily have run into; for his Sense will be plainly this, <hi>That if I profess to have a Rule for my Faith and Practice, by Immediate Inspiration, I ought to evidence to him who denies and rejects it, that this Rule of mine is from Heaven, before I my self have walked by it,</hi> or <hi>made any Observation of it.</hi> A Position so <hi>ridiculous,</hi> that it was sit on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for <hi>T. Plant</hi> to publish, <hi>who has the worst luck in writing Notes,</hi> of any Man that I have read.</p>
               <p>But sayes <hi>J. Ives</hi> p. 100. <q rend="inline">
                     <hi>You may soon have as much Evidence as we for Immediate Inspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; for we never pretended to it, as a Rule for our Faith and Practice, in the <hi>Christian</hi> Religion.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Observ.</label> If by WE he intends the whole People call'd <hi>Baptists, he speaks untruly;</hi> for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them did <hi>formerly</hi> own the <hi>Teachings and Guidance of the Spirit,</hi> and asserted it in their Writings: But if he restrain his WE to those of them who are concern'd in the present Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troversie with us, I must then say unto him and them, O <hi>how are ye degenerated from your An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cestors in Religion!</hi> How different is a <hi>Baptist</hi> now, from what a <hi>Baptist</hi> then was! Were not your Predecessors called in Derision <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thusiasts</hi>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:204828:37"/> (as ye now call us) <hi>because they then contended for</hi> (that which you now deny, <hi>viz.</hi>) <hi>The Divine Teachings and Immediate Assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of the Holy Spirit, in their Preaching and ex tempore Praying?</hi> Were they not called <hi>Gifted Brethren,</hi> from their affirming, <hi>they had received the Gift of the Holy Ghost?</hi> Look back into Dr. <hi>Featly</hi>'s Book, called, DIPPERS DIPT, printed in the Year, 1645. Turn over <hi>R. Capenter</hi>'s Book, entituled THE ANABAPTIST WASHT AND WASHT, AND SHRUNK IN THE WASHING, and see if these Things were not so: But these perhaps you will say, were your Adversa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; therefore I will put you in Mind of some of your Brethren: Read <hi>Edward Barber</hi>'s DISCOVERY OF THE MINISTRY OF THE GOSPEL (printed <hi>Anno</hi> 1645. Look into <hi>Daniel King</hi>'s WAY TO SION, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he affirms, That <q rend="inline">
                     <hi>by the MOTION OF THE SPIRIT he that is call'd to be a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister, may and ought to Baptize as well as Preach,</hi> p. 89.</q> Examine <hi>T. Collier</hi>'s Works, particularly his MARROW OF CHRISTI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ANITY, and his EPISTLE TO ALL THE SAINTS; in which last he sayes (chap. 12. p. 52.) <q rend="inline">
                     <hi>The Spirit of God, who is God, is the ALONE RƲLE of a spiritual Christian.</hi>
                  </q> Peruse <hi>Samuel How</hi>'s Treatise, entitul'd, THE
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:204828:37"/> SUFFICIENCY OF THE SPIRIT'S TEA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHING, &amp;c. wherein he will tell you, <hi>p.</hi> 21. <q rend="inline">
                     <hi>
                        <hi>That</hi> the Glory of Christ's Doctrine is, that it is of the SPIRIT'S TEACHING: for when <hi>(adds he)</hi> we behold the Glory of the Lord in the most perfect Measure, so as we are chang'd thereinto from Glory to Glory; yet ALL IS FROM THE SPIRIT OF THE LORD, seeing that he is the promised Comforter, that is to TEACH ƲS ALL GOOD THINGS belonging to our Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Examine these Quotations, &amp; call to mind the former Dayes, and then tell me, whether ye have not herein deny'd the Testimonies of your Brethren, who so honestly asserted, and zealously contended for the <hi>inward Working, Teaching &amp; Guidance of the holy Spirit,</hi> which you now disdainfully and contemptuously re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject. Many other Testimonies, of this kind, I could add; but I forbear, in Hopes of a future Opportunity to expostulate this Case a little more fully with you: At this time therefore, I will only add the Judgment of <hi>William Kiffin,</hi> a Man of no mean Repute amongst you, and now living; He, in his <hi>Postscript</hi> to <hi>Sam. How</hi>'s fore-mention'd Book, exprest himself thus, <q rend="inline">
                     <hi>But my Intent in writing this Hard Word <hi>(which respected some Hardship &amp; Ignominy
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:204828:38"/> the Author had undergone)</hi> 'is not to commend the Author, but to tender to thy Review the matter of this foregoing Book, the Bent there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is, to advance the TEACHINGS OF THE SPIRIT of Christ, in the Ʋnfolding of the Mystery of the Gospel to the Hearts of Men, as the CHOICE REVEALER of that Glory of Truth to the Soul, which will change from Glory to Glory into its own Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, a TRƲTH much opposed by MEN OF CORRƲPT MINDS in this Day.</hi>
                  </q> Thus far <hi>W. Kiffin</hi> about 20 Years ago: From which, <hi>Reader,</hi> thou may'st observe, That they who <hi>opposed the Teachings of the Spirit of Christ in the Ʋnfolding of the Mystery of the Gospel to the Hearts of men, as the choice Revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of the Glory of Truth to the Soul,</hi> were by <hi>W. Kiffin</hi> accounted and called <hi>Men of corrupt Minds</hi> at that Day: What manner of Minds he and his Brethren now have, who so confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently oppose and furiously contend against this Truth at this Day, I leave to thee to infer.</p>
               <p>In p. 102. <hi>W.P.</hi> tells them, <hi>That the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs in Q.</hi> Marys <hi>Dayes, had the Testimony of the Lord within them, and though they could not dispute for their Religion, yet they could burn and suffer for it.</hi> To this <hi>J. Ives</hi> answers, <hi>But they were no</hi> Quakers (what if they were not call'd <hi>Quakers?</hi> He will grant they were <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians,</hi>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:204828:38"/> and <hi>that is enough;</hi> for the Consequence is plain, that <hi>they who have the Inward Testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of the Lord within them, are true</hi> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians, <hi>though they give no external Evidence of it</hi>) Here again <hi>T. Plant</hi> calls upon his Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to note; <hi>Note, Reader</hi> (sayes he) <hi>how these Men can own the Martyrs in Q.</hi> Marys <hi>Dayes for</hi> Christians, <hi>and yet in these Dayes own none to be</hi> Christians <hi>but themselves, is a Paradox.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Observ.</label>
                  <hi>First,</hi> I put him to prove who of us hath said, we own none to be <hi>Christians,</hi> but our selves. <hi>Next,</hi> I say, that if that should be suppos'd, yet it would be <hi>no Paradox at all.</hi> And I ask <hi>T. Plant</hi> whether or no the <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants,</hi> when first they protested against the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> might not have said, <hi>that they owned the Apostles and primitive Church to be</hi> Christians; <hi>but yet that they owned none in the Dayes wherein themselves lived to be</hi> Christians <hi>but themselves, and this without any Paradox at all?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He goes on thus, <hi>Did the Martyrs in Q.</hi> Marys <hi>Dayes pretend to Immediate Inspiration for the Rule of their Faith and Practice? if not, what a grand Piece of Impertinency is it to name them upon this Occasion, who pretended to no other Rule for their Faith and Practice, then the Holy Scriptures?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:204828:39"/>
               <p>
                  <label>Observ.</label> They did pretend to Immediate Inspiration, and yet <hi>were no Impostors</hi> neither. <hi>John Bradford,</hi> a Man eminent amongst them, both for his Piety and Learning, in his Answer to the Arch-Bishop of <hi>York,</hi> sayes thus, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrol. 3. Vol. 3. p. 296. <q rend="inline">
                     <hi>We do believe and know the Scriptures, as Christ's Sheep, not because the Church saith, they are the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, but because they be so, being thereof as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sur'd by the same Spirit that spake them.</hi>
                  </q> Hence it is evident, that the Holy Spirit, or <hi>Divine Inspiration, was the Rule of this Godly Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr's Faith,</hi> even concerning the Scriptures themselves And <hi>John Philpot</hi> another Godly and Learned Martyr, having in the Beginning of his Bible written this Sentence, <hi>Spiritus est vicarius Christi in terris.</hi> i. e. <hi>The Spirit is Christ's Vicar</hi> (or in Christ's stead) <hi>on Earth;</hi> gave this Answer to <hi>B. Bonner</hi> enquiring the Reason of his so Writing: <q rend="inline">
                     <hi>Christ since his As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cension worketh all things in us by his Spirit, and by his Spirit doth dwell in us, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </q> Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrol. Vol. 3. p. 573. To the same Purpose writes <hi>William Tindal</hi> (another eminent and worthy Martyr) in his Answer to <hi>More</hi>'s Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alogue: <q rend="inline">
                     <hi>When <hi>(sayes he)</hi> thou art asked, why thou believest thou shalt be saved by Christ? answer, thou feelest that it is true; <hi>and when he asketh, how thou knowest it is true? an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer,</hi>
                        <pb n="77" facs="tcp:204828:39"/> because it is written in thy Heart; <hi>if he ask, who wrote it? answer,</hi> the Spirit of God; <hi>if he ask, how thou camest first by it? tell him,</hi> thou wast INWARDLY TAƲGHT by the Spirit of God; <hi>and if he ask, whether thou believest it not, because it is written in Books, or because the Priests so preach? answer,</hi> No, not now, but only because it is written in thy Heart, and because the Spirit of God so preacheth, and so testifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth unto thy Soul, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </q> Thus far <hi>Tindal,</hi> by which the Reader may see, how much this god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Martyr was for the immediate Teachings of the Holy Spirit in the Hearts of God's People, <hi>which is the very same Thing we contend for at this Day,</hi> and for which these quarelling <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tists</hi> now revile us. To these let me add the Testimony of <hi>John Jewel,</hi> that zealous and learned Defender of the <hi>Protestant</hi> Religion, who though no Martyr, yet lived much about the same Time: He against <hi>Harding</hi> main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, <q rend="inline">
                     <hi>That without the SPECIAL Help, Prompting and REVELATION of God's Holy Spirit, the Scriptures are to the Reader, be he never so wise or well-learned, as the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of a sealed Book.</hi>
                  </q> From these few Instan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, let the Reader judge, whether the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs owned Immediate Inspiration, or the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:204828:40"/> Teachings, Promptings and Revelation of God's Spirit, or not.</p>
               <p>But <hi>T. Plant</hi> adds, That <hi>the Consciences of the Martyrs were perswaded of the Authority of the Scriptures,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Observ.</label> I no way doubt it: But the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion is, <hi>What that was by which their Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences were so perswaded; whether it was divine Inspiration, the Manifestation or Revelation of God's Holy Spirit or not?</hi> If, Reader, the Testimonies of the Martyrs themselves will be taken, those before cited are plain and full. <hi>Tindal</hi> believed his Salvation by Christ, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause he felt the Truth and Certainty thereof, written in his Heart by the Spirit of God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing inwardly taught by the same Spirit:</hi> He believed not because it was writen in Books, or preacht by Man, but <hi>because he found it written in his own Heart, and felt the Spirit of God so preaching and testifying unto his Soul. Jewel</hi> denies the Scriptures to be intelligible <hi>without the ESPECIAL Help, Prompting and REVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LATION of God's Holy Spirit.</hi> Bradford, <hi>in the Name of all the rest,</hi> sayes, <hi>We do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve and know the Scriptures, as Christ's Sheep, being thereof assured by the same Spirit that spake them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thou seest now Reader, that the Conscien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:204828:40"/> of the godly Martyrs were perswaded, <hi>or rather assured</hi> of the Verity and Authority of the Holy Scriptures, <hi>by immediate Inspiration</hi> or the <hi>Revelation of the Divine Spirit in their own Hearts,</hi> wherein their Testimony most <hi>sweetly harmonizes</hi> with ours.</p>
               <p>There is one Clause more in <hi>T. Plant</hi>'s Note, which peradventure may deserve the Reader's Notice: It is this, <hi>Had the Martyrs</hi> (sayes he) <hi>lived in our Dayes, they would have run the same Hazard</hi> (to wit, of their Lives) <hi>if cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led thereunto, to oppose</hi> Quakerism, <hi>as they did then to oppose</hi> Popery.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Observ.</label> Two things herein seem observable: One, that <hi>T. Plant</hi> supposes <hi>they must have had a Call to it,</hi> before they had run so great an Hazard, and thereby <hi>he lets in Revelation or immediate Inspiration,</hi> before he is aware of it. The other is, <hi>That he who so scornfully denies Revelation, pretends here himself to understand what they that were dead above an Hundred Years ago, would have done, if they had been alive now.</hi> Here his Confidence hath betray'd him: He is a desperate Enemy to Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and yet <hi>takes upon him to tell Things, not otherwise knowable▪ then by Revelation.</hi> Doth he speak by Rote? <hi>Parrats</hi> do so: Has he certain Knowledge of what he pake? <hi>How came he by it?</hi> Has he no certain Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:204828:41"/> but only bare Conjecture, <hi>why then so confident? why so positive?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Relation of the Meeting being ended, <hi>T. Plant</hi> goes on to give his Reader an Account of some Letters that passed between them and us, in order to the appointing of another. In these Letters it was proposed, <hi>That five of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Side should meet, to consult of such Things as necessarily related thereunto: Accordingly,</hi> (saith he) <hi>Mr.</hi> Kiffin, <hi>Mr.</hi> Dyke, <hi>Mr.</hi> Paul, <hi>Mr.</hi> Snelling, <hi>Mr.</hi> King <hi>and</hi> Mr. <hi>PLANT did meet,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Observ.</label> One would think <hi>T. Plant</hi> had an <hi>itching Humor</hi> to be called MASTER, else he would never call himself so; and yet this is not the first time (see <hi>p.</hi> 71. 74.) that he hath befool'd himself with that Title: But let him injoy his Humor, if he please; I would not too severely perstringe him, but leave him to <hi>the Correction of his own Folly,</hi> and proceed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>They met,</hi> he sayes, <hi>with</hi> W. Mead, J. Os<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>good, W. Welch, <hi>and several others, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated the Proposals which they had sent to us,</hi> and printed (which were New and different from those that had been mutually agreed on between them and us before, &amp; upon which the former Meeting was held) and <hi>Mr. Kiffin,</hi> he sayes, <hi>and the rest did urge, that we should pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:204828:41"/> in that Method as is exprest in the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said Proposals: Ʋpon this,</hi> he saith, <hi>the</hi> Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers <hi>manifested some Suspicion of the Proposals, as they were worded, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Observ.</label> Had they not <hi>good Cause</hi> so to do? Was it probable you would <hi>fly off from the old Proposals,</hi> which you had so freely and readily (as you intimate, <hi>p.</hi> 13.) consented to and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced, if he had not had <hi>Hopes,</hi> in obtruding New ones, to <hi>advantage</hi> your selves, and <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jure</hi> us? If you thought, we took you for our <hi>Friends,</hi> you were very much <hi>mistaken:</hi> and truly, not much less, if considering you as <hi>Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,</hi> and such too from whom, <hi>Experience had taught us,</hi> we were not to look for <hi>sincere and generous Dealing,</hi> ye expected we should treat you without that <hi>prudent Caution</hi> and Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spection, which is requisit in such Cases.</p>
               <p>But <hi>W. Welch,</hi> he sayes, <hi>produc'd a Paper, that crost all they had discoursed before:</hi> And what was that? Why, <hi>It was an Answer,</hi> he sayes, <hi>to their Proposals: Whereupon,</hi> saith he, <hi>W. Kiffin and those with him, seeing such disin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuous Dealing, did conclude, 'twas to no Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose to treat any longer with them, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Observ.</label> By this, Reader, thou may'st see <hi>how hearty these men were in their Treaty for another Meeting,</hi> who could catch hold of such a <hi>trivial Occasion</hi> to break off, and treat no
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:204828:42"/> more. Doubtless these <hi>Baptists</hi> are very <hi>touchy</hi> and <hi>pettish</hi> (or else <hi>they were weary of the Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siness</hi>) for I observe in their Relation of the first Meeting, <hi>pag.</hi> 25. They say, <hi>They could gain no direct Answer,</hi> and that <hi>there-upon</hi> J. Ives <hi>and</hi> T. Hicks <hi>withdrew.</hi> It is a Sign they were <hi>in Haste to be gone,</hi> when the bare giving of an Answer, which they judg'd not direct (had it been so) would drive them away. Though when they say, <hi>the Answer was</hi> not direct, <hi>to their Design</hi> is to be understood; for to the Question it was direct and plain: But their Aim being to render us obnoxious to the People, as Persons denying the <hi>Man Christ Jesus,</hi> our Answer thwarting their Expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, fully and clearly proved that <hi>We own him;</hi> This, say they, <hi>is not direct</hi> (viz <hi>to their Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose</hi>) and this Disappointment must be sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed to give them so great an Offence, that away they <hi>fling;</hi> no holding, no stopping them, no Perswasion, nor Entreaty may prevail with them to tarry. One would think they might have stay'd at least so long, as to have shown the People the <hi>Indirectness</hi> of the Answer: No, they were <hi>in too great Haste</hi> to stay. They wanted some <hi>colourable</hi> Pretence for a <hi>Retreat;</hi> and though this was a very sorry one, yet better <hi>came off thus, then worse; for the Battle went sore against them.</hi> And much after
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:204828:42"/> the same manner were <hi>W. Kiffin, T. Plant,</hi> and the rest of them <hi>put to it,</hi> to get off from this Treaty for another Meeting. 'Tis worth thy observing, <hi>Reader,</hi> how they were put to their <hi>Shifts</hi> for an <hi>Excuse: W. Welch,</hi> they say, <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd a Paper, containing an Answer to their Proposals, and this,</hi> they say, <hi>crost all they had discoursed before; whereupon</hi> W. Kiffin, <hi>and those with him, seeing such disingenuous Deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, did conclude, it was to no Purpose to treat any longer with them.</hi> This was that they had <hi>a mind to be at;</hi> but could they have chosen a worse <hi>Medium</hi> to have <hi>come off by?</hi> Would any but themselves have broke off a Treaty, <hi>because an Answer was offer'd to their Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sals?</hi> Do ye <hi>Baptists</hi> account it disingenuous Dealing <hi>to return an Answer to your Proposals?</hi> Why then, Oh disingenuo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Men! did you make such Proposals as <hi>ye were not willing</hi> to receive an Answer to? How truly may I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tort upon your selves that which <hi>J. Ives</hi> most untruly reflects upon us, <hi>p.</hi> 113. Ye are resol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved <hi>to find Fault with any thing, Right or Wrong, &amp;c.</hi> For ye refus'd before to treat with us, because (as ye say, but falsly, <hi>p.</hi> 30, 41, 42.) <hi>we took no Notice of your Proposals;</hi> and now, that ye might fly off from the present Treaty, ye <hi>pick a Quarrel</hi> with us, because <hi>we offer you an Answer to your Proposals:</hi> What <hi>ticklish
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:204828:43"/> People</hi> have we to deal with? How is it pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible to satisfie such men, who are <hi>never pleas'd full nor fasting?</hi> who, if they are <hi>not answer'd,</hi> will <hi>not treat</hi> at all; and if they <hi>are answer'd,</hi> will thereupon <hi>break off,</hi> and treat no more: But this I doubt not, will satisfie all indifferent Readers, that you have hitherto but <hi>praevari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated with us,</hi> and not acted <hi>sincerely</hi> and cordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, so far as ye have already treated. But to go on.</p>
               <p>To our <hi>Answer</hi> to their printed Proposals they sent us a <hi>Reply,</hi> and thereto we return'd them a <hi>Rejoynder:</hi> Their <hi>Reply</hi> T. Plant hath <hi>printed at large;</hi> but unfairly omitted our <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joynder,</hi> giving his Reader but three or four Lines of the <hi>Close</hi> of it, and <hi>concealing</hi> all the rest, which was as followeth:</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>London</hi>
                           <date>the 24th 8th Month, 1674.</date>
                        </dateline>
                     </opener>
                     <p>Your's bearing <hi>Date</hi> the 22th Instant, we have received and consider'd, and return you these Observations upon it: What you mean <hi>by antedating our Paper, and Jeering thereupon,</hi> you shew us not, whatever you suggest, it bears the <hi>Date</hi> of the <hi>same Day,</hi> on which it was first drawn up, <hi>viz.</hi> the 17th Instant, being <hi>the Day after the Meeting at</hi> Wheeler Street, though not delivered to you so soon, because our Friends did not understand, that those of
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:204828:43"/> you they treated with, either <hi>had Power, or were willing to conclude a Meeting without some more of your Friends or Assistants:</hi> However, our Paper was in <hi>Answer to your Printed Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posals,</hi> and as we judged necessary and reaso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable. Our saying, <hi>We condescended to return you that Answer to your Proposals, was not to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alt our selves as Superiors, or as Lofty, or Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perious;</hi> but that it was a Condescension to propose <hi>Terms for a private Meeting</hi> with you, since we reckoned and knew our selves so pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly injur'd by you, in abetting or counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancing a <hi>Forger.</hi> As for your treating with us, as <hi>Persons departed from the</hi> Christian <hi>Faith,</hi> you might have suspended that Judgment till we had come to a Tryal, since that <hi>your</hi> Charge <hi>therein is yet to prove</hi> (however you doubt not to do it) and <hi>T. Hicks</hi> his <hi>Reasons</hi> for it are yet to be debated: As also your Purpose to prove us, <hi>whether we are Subverters of the</hi> Christian <hi>Religion, or not,</hi> is but a profest <hi>Purpose,</hi> not yet performed nor accomplisht; so that how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, <hi>neither</hi> Tho. Hicks <hi>in his Dialogues, nor</hi> Jer. Ives <hi>in his Syllogistical Attempts</hi> have yet <hi>proved</hi> us such, although <hi>pretended</hi> by both; their Labour and Time hitherto is then mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spent, and yet you will boast, <hi>as if we were pincht, apparently worsted, and used silly Shifts:</hi> This savours of <hi>Tho. Hicks</hi>'s Spirit, with much
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:204828:44"/> more in your perverse and peevish Letter, a your upbraiding us with such Words and Phra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses as these, viz. <q rend="inline">
                           <hi>Palpable Equivocations, your Folly, manifest Lyars, guilty Persons, your common Way of Triffling, Persons departed from the <hi>Christian</hi> Faith, <hi>and your Insinuation as if we were</hi> afraid of a fair Tryal, and seem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to dread nothing more then that <hi>T. Hicks</hi> should speak for himself,</hi>
                        </q> which is as true as that 'tis not the Argument, but the Man we would deal with, whenas both our <hi>Answers to</hi> Tho. Hicks <hi>and our Proposals for a Meeting</hi> with him, to examine Matters, evidently shew the contrary: Have we refused him to give his <hi>Arguments</hi> in those Matters we have char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged against him? Or have we not manifested both our Willingness and Desire therein? will such <hi>Falshoods</hi> gain you or him Credit in the Minds of the Unbyassed? We perceive <hi>you are not now fit, either for a further Treaty, or a private Meting:</hi> You appear so perverse, as Men leavened with your Agent <hi>Tho. Hicks</hi> his Spirit, or that had swallowed down some of his Cholerick, Humor or Passion (but there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, neither he nor you will bring Honour to your Cause) And therefore 'tis necessary that we consider of some other Way further to throw off his <hi>Dirt, Calumnies, Slanders</hi> and <hi>Forgeries,</hi> and therewithal to endeavour to
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:204828:44"/> manifest your corrupt <hi>Partiality,</hi> in abetting such an Agent, if you will afford us no <hi>better Treating</hi> then is in this <hi>angry, scornful, boasting and upraiding Letter of yours;</hi> however, if we should be mute, and suffer all your <hi>Abuses</hi> in silence, we doubt not but the Just God will bring a Stroke upon you, for your <hi>Injustice</hi> and <hi>Partiality.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But to your <hi>Exceptions</hi> against our <hi>Proposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> in Answer to yours.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. Where in our second we provide a <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, that such as have a Necessity on their Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits to speak briefly to the Business in hand,</hi> which Liberty we granted you as well as our selves: This you say, <hi>You cannot admit of</hi> (neither can we admit of your <hi>Exception</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst it) and also for your Reason, falsly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cusing us, as that <hi>you know it is ordinary with us (when pincht) to pretend a Motion to divert from the Point in hand;</hi> and also infer (though from a false Surmise of your own, no waies consequent to what we propose) <hi>that the same Necessity might be pleaded to talk all the time as well as briefly to the Matter in hand.</hi> Say you so? Then you will not believe what we say; if you must be our <hi>Judges,</hi> no less then the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation due to <hi>Equivocators,</hi> is to be expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted from you: By this you have very much bewray'd your own <hi>covertly and feign'd Work,</hi>
                        <pb n="88" facs="tcp:204828:45"/> in endeavouring <hi>to bind us to Terms and Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sals,</hi> when now you render us no better then Persons not to be credited. We cannot under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take to purchase a <hi>Meeting</hi> with you at such a difficult Rate, as the <hi>Removal of your hard Thoughts first:</hi> However, you would make a fair <hi>Shew</hi> to the World as if you were in <hi>Ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest</hi> to have Matters fairly tryed between us; but such <hi>Covers</hi> will prove too narrow.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Though you could not comply with our Answer to your <hi>sixth Proposal,</hi> with respect to the <hi>Day</hi> and <hi>Hour;</hi> yet with respect to the Conclusion <hi>to end with Consent,</hi> you might ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well have comply'd with it, and not have prejudg'd our Intention, as if we <hi>design'd to call you</hi> Fugitives <hi>&amp;</hi> Run-awayes, <hi>if you should depart in your time:</hi> The Lord knows, we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign'd no such thing; but that after we had met a convenient Time, on a fair or seasonable Proposal for a parting, it might be consented unto: However, your Cause is attended with many <hi>Distrustful Thoughts, Jealousies</hi> and <hi>evil Surmises</hi> against us, which at least would ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der your Cause very <hi>suspicious</hi> to us, if we had not that Inspection into it that we have.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. From our saying (in Answer to your 7th) <hi>That if we find by the first Meeting that you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign to do us Right in as publick a manner as</hi> T. Hicks <hi>hath done us Wrong, &amp;c. that then we
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:204828:45"/> will consider of another Meeting,</hi> you unjustly infer from hence, that <hi>this is as much as to say, that if</hi> T. Hicks <hi>should acquit himself, and you publickly clear him, and condemn us as</hi> Slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers, &amp;c. <hi>then we will meet no more with you, lest our Tenets should be too openly exposed and discovered:</hi> This is like one of <hi>T. Hicks</hi>'s Consequences; whereas our Answer implies no such Jealousie of our selves as condemnable, nor any Doubt or Question of making good our <hi>Charge</hi> against <hi>T. Hicks,</hi> but the contrary, as not at all questioning but that we should make his <hi>fraudulent Dealing</hi> and <hi>Guilt</hi> appear obvious to your Understandings; only we had Reason to question your <hi>Design</hi> towards us: However we were willing to make some Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gress in order to try you further, as is plain by what we have proposed.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. Our <hi>Exception</hi> against your 9th <hi>Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sal,</hi> as being unreasonable, you are pleased to call <hi>ridiculous and impertinent Reasoning;</hi> and why so? Is it because we might not be oblig'd <hi>aforehand to answer</hi> T. Hicks<hi>'s Charges against us,</hi> when they were never <hi>specified</hi> to us; nor <hi>He a competent Person</hi> to prosecute us, <hi>after our Charge is proved against him,</hi> which we no waies doubted to do, if we might but have Opportunity? But to excuse your Agent as a <hi>competent Person to prosecute us,</hi> you say, <hi>Were
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:204828:46"/> it supposed (though as yet you see no Reason to grant) that in some things</hi> T. Hicks <hi>might be mistaken, it will not therefore-follow, that every thing he saith, ought not to be credited:</hi> Though we grant this; yet herein you do but <hi>mince and cover,</hi> and are egregiously <hi>besides our Charge</hi> and Provision against <hi>T. Hicks;</hi> for it is not that he may be or is <hi>in some things</hi> meerly <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der some Mistake,</hi> and therefore <hi>not competent,</hi> but that <hi>he is a vile Forger, Perverter &amp; Slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer,</hi> and that <hi>in many things:</hi> This is the <hi>Nature of our Charge</hi> already proved against him in two Books, <hi>Reason against Railing,</hi> and <hi>The Counterfeit</hi> Christian <hi>detected,</hi> which we are apt to think that you have not read over, or seriously perused (for if you had, we think you would have better acquiesced with our <hi>Charge</hi> against him, without giving us further Occasion to pursue it) You do so mince and <hi>lessen</hi> matters that are closely laid and charg'd against <hi>T. H.</hi> From [<hi>a vile Forger,</hi> &amp;c.] you would have it turned to [<hi>were it supposed that in some things</hi> T. H. <hi>might be mistaken, which as yet you see no Reason to grant</hi>] It seems then that he is a very <hi>Ʋnerring Person</hi> in your E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steem; but we desire both <hi>J. Ives</hi> and the rest of you, but seriously to read over the last Book of <hi>W. Penn</hi>'s, in Answer to him intitul'd, <hi>The Counterfeit Christian detected,</hi> and then consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:204828:46"/> whether all these things which he is chargd with, are only <hi>supposed</hi> Mistakes. Your Retor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion upon <hi>G. Whitehead</hi> and <hi>W. Penn,</hi> as <hi>not competent Persons to prosecute</hi> T. H. <hi>for the like Reason that we have given against him,</hi> viz. <hi>That they do not only stand accused for, but in convenient time will be prov'd manifest Lyars.</hi> It seems <hi>T. Hicks</hi> has not yet <hi>prov'd them</hi> such; that is yet to do: but we observe, he is much <hi>lowder</hi> and fiercer in his <hi>Charges,</hi> then in his <hi>Proofs.</hi> But do you really now judge <hi>G.W.</hi> and <hi>W. P.</hi> cannot be compleat <hi>Persons to prosecute our Charge</hi> against <hi>T. Hicks?</hi> If you do, you should have told us that at first; why then did you admit of a <hi>Meeting</hi> with them at all on that account, in order <hi>to make good their Charg?</hi> Hath <hi>T. Hicks</hi> devised this as <hi>a Hole to creep out at, and save his Head?</hi> But such retorting <hi>Shifts</hi> will not clear him, or you either. However, before either <hi>G. W.</hi> or <hi>W. P.</hi> be obliged to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer to <hi>T. Hicks</hi>'s Charges against them, they expect a <hi>Note</hi> from him <hi>of the Particulars that he grounds his Charge upon,</hi> as we have done by him, at some of your Desires.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. Touching our <hi>Assenting,</hi> that when we have done with <hi>T. H.</hi> about matters of <hi>Fact</hi> charg'd, and that you have done us <hi>Justice</hi> therein, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> we should be willing, if the Lord will, as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient Opportunity may be afforded to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:204828:47"/> matters of <hi>Doctrine</hi> with some others of you, &amp;c. you unreasonably quarrel with the Words <hi>[as convenient Opportunity may be]</hi> as signifying our <hi>common way of Triffling,</hi> as you falsly and scornfully say; whereas we seri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously expressed our real Intentions and Desires therein, as not having Time and <hi>convenient Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity</hi> in our own hands to command, that being in the Hand and Disposal of an omnisci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent God, whom we fear, and in Subjection to whose Will we propose Matters that are not in our present Time and Will to be done.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. Touching our <hi>Willingness</hi> to discourse matters of <hi>Doctrine</hi> with some <hi>more competent, &amp;c.</hi> you ask, <hi>Why not with you? Why not with T. Hicks?</hi> We think that we have offer'd suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Reason, at least, supposing if <hi>T.H.</hi> appear <hi>guilty of that Charge</hi> laid against him and you Abettors of him, being such a guilty Person, <hi>a vile Forger, &amp;c.</hi> this would render you all <hi>incompetent and unmeet to discourse of the things of God's Kingdom;</hi> would it not, suppose you?</p>
                     <p n="7">7. We now fully understand you (as we per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived your Design before) <hi>that as ye,</hi> say you, <hi>yielded that those matters wherein</hi> G. Keith <hi>was concern'd should be spoaken unto, provided that afterwards the Paper of</hi> Charges <hi>be next spoa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken unto; and desire that one Article may be issued before any other be insisted on;</hi> as namely,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:204828:47"/>
                        <hi>That you shall not admit of any Discourse upon other Particulars after</hi> G. Keith's <hi>Business is issued till those Reasons which</hi> T. Hicks <hi>hath given why he opposeth the</hi> Christian <hi>to the</hi> Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, <hi>be fully debated:</hi> We cannot but take it for granted, that still you put us off with dila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory <hi>Evasions,</hi> to keep us from pursuing our <hi>Charge,</hi> contrary to what we have offer'd, and you in words pretended; and <hi>what Delay and Time</hi> this fully Debating of <hi>T. Hicks</hi>'s said Reasons <hi>will require,</hi> who knows? Thus you <hi>triffle</hi> with us: Have we not plainly proposed and offer'd to discourse matters of <hi>Doctrine</hi> in their place, when matters of <hi>Fact</hi> are <hi>gone through:</hi> yea, and have openly declared our <hi>Willingness</hi> to discourse those <hi>Reasons</hi> on which you pretend to prove us <hi>no Christians,</hi> in their place; for the <hi>Stress</hi> of our first Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle is <hi>not</hi> upon <hi>T.H</hi>'s opposing the <hi>Christian</hi> to the <hi>Quaker;</hi> but upon <hi>A Dialogue</hi> betwixt a Christian and a Quaker, <hi>yet</hi> made by <hi>T. H.</hi> 1st, <hi>Was it made and contrived by</hi> T. Hicks, <hi>Yea, or Nay?</hi> Or, <hi>Was it a</hi> real Dialogue <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween a</hi> Quaker <hi>and any Body else?</hi> If not, <hi>then</hi> 2dly, <hi>Hath he said</hi> True, <hi>in positively</hi> calling it so, <hi>and telling the World in his very Title-page, that</hi> therein is faithfully represented <hi>the chief and most concerning Opinions of the</hi> Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, <hi>together with their Method and Manner
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:204828:48"/> of Reasoning in Defence thereof?</hi> We affirm this to be <hi>False,</hi> and would have produc'd ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Instances to have prov'd it so, even out of <hi>T. H</hi>'s own <hi>Dialogues:</hi> But you will needs have him in the first place give his <hi>Reasons, why he opposeth the</hi> Quaker <hi>to the</hi> Christian, which is not the thing we in that place either com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of, or in that Article affirm that the <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker</hi> is a <hi>Christian</hi> (though in its place we have confest it and shall) but <hi>T. Hicks,</hi> the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triver and Maker of the Dialogue, <hi>makes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self that</hi> Christian <hi>that dialogues with the</hi> Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker (as he calls him) and he is both call'd and prov'd <hi>Counterfeit Christian,</hi> or <hi>no Christian;</hi> and it is our parts rather to <hi>prove him so,</hi> then his to <hi>prove us none;</hi> when it is not the matter complained on by us in the first place, but he is positively charg'd to be <hi>A vile Forger, &amp;c.</hi> neither doth the <hi>Stress</hi> of our Complaint lie upon the <hi>first Article;</hi> that's placed but as an Introduction into the following matter, &amp; hath been of this service, that many who thought they were <hi>real Dialogues,</hi> now understand they are but <hi>fictitious.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To conclude; We do not only take it for granted that you are now further off from a Compliance then you seem'd before; but also that you are afraid that your <hi>Brother T. Hicks</hi> should come to a <hi>plain Test</hi> or <hi>Tryal upon our
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:204828:48"/> direct Charge,</hi> lest the Consequence reflect on your selves: We see that you except against six or seven material Passages in our Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sals, and we see no Reason why we should fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther condescend to your dilatory Work, but to consider some other Way or Expedient to clear our selves, especially since you have so much prejudged us.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <list>
                              <item>George Whitehead,</item>
                              <item>George Keith,</item>
                              <item>Jasper Batt.</item>
                           </list>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>This they return'd no Answer to, nor have since made any Overture to resume the <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> which in a <hi>pettish Humor</hi> they had broken off; And yet they would fain make People believe, they are <hi>not unwilling to give us a Meeting:</hi> Yet when they say, <hi>p.</hi> 107. <hi>Could such a Meeting be peaceably obtain'd, we should gladly attend it,</hi> they sufficiently discover e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to common Capacities, how <hi>Cold</hi> they are in their Desires of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:204828:49"/>
               <head>CHAP. IIII. Some Animadversions upon <hi>J. Ives</hi>'s Postscript.</head>
               <p>THat which comes next under my Consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration is, a Postscript added to <hi>Tho. Plant</hi>'s Book, and subscribed by <hi>Jer. Ives,</hi> in the Introduction to which he tells his Reader, That <q rend="inline">
                     <hi>the <hi>Quakers</hi> have no more Cause to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, then <hi>Caligula</hi>'s Souldiers, who had nothing but Cocle-shells to shew, for the Trophies and Spoils of their great Victories.</hi>
                  </q> Hence first I infer, that <hi>he grants the Victory may be great, though the Trophies and Spoils are but small.</hi> Next, I desire the Reader to consider, what <hi>Sort of People</hi> we had to war withal, to wit, <hi>Such as deny the immediate Assistance of the holy Spirit,</hi> Such <hi>as scoff at divine Inspira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion &amp; Revelation,</hi> Men <hi>whose Religion stands in outward Performances, whose Treasure lies in External Shews and Outside Appearances, preferring the</hi> SHELL <hi>before the Substance:</hi> If therefore our <hi>Spoiles</hi> consist of <hi>SHELLS,</hi> wonder not, <hi>Reader,</hi> at it: but rather that <hi>so many</hi> Knowing Men, should be grown <hi>Gray-Headed</hi> in a Profession of Religion, and yet
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:204828:49"/>
                  <hi>have nothing but</hi> SHELLS <hi>to loose.</hi> But from this I attend him to his <hi>Observations.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the first he sayes, <q rend="inline">
                     <hi>It is observable that most of the Time spent in the two Dayes Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences, was to prevail upon them to hear our Arguments, to prove they were no <hi>Christians,</hi> and that their Ministers were Cheats and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postors.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>This from his own pen, doth us great Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice: for having fully (as I conceive) demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strated before, that this was not the <hi>Subject</hi> agreed upon, nor the proper Business of those two Dayes; but that it was <hi>our Charge</hi> against <hi>T. Hicks,</hi> consisting of FORGERY, PER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VERSIONS, FALSHOODS, SLANDERS, &amp;c. that was the proper Subject and Business of those dayes, which it concern'd <hi>Ʋs</hi> to prove <hi>against him,</hi> not <hi>he</hi> or they <hi>against us</hi> (for we were the Opponents, they the Respondents, and <hi>J. Ives</hi> himself will not admit <hi>that a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spondent should offer to prove,</hi> see <hi>pag.</hi> 81. of <hi>T. Plant</hi>'s Relation) that, I say, being before hand sufficiently demonstrated, this open con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession of <hi>Jer. Ives,</hi> that <hi>most of the Time in the two Dayes Conferences, was spent to prevail up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us, to hear their Arguments to prove us no</hi> Christians, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> doth put it out of all Question that it was <hi>They declined</hi> the Subject to be
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:204828:50"/> proved, <hi>not We;</hi> though <hi>T. Plant</hi> most un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>handsomly, as well as falsly hath charged it upon us, <hi>pag.</hi> 36.</p>
               <p>But this <hi>Jer. Ives</hi> saith, <hi>They conceived rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable;</hi> and he offers some Reasons for it: <q rend="inline">
                     <hi>First, <hi>saith he,</hi> because it was contained in the first Article of their written Charge, sent in against <hi>T. Hicks,</hi> which was for writing a Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue, and opposing a <hi>Christian</hi> to a <hi>Quaker.</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reader,</hi> That thou may'st satisfie thy self, that in this Instance <hi>Jer. Ives</hi> hath <hi>not dealt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestly</hi> with us, nor fairly with thee, I refer thee to the <hi>Charge</hi> it self, as it stands in their own Book, <hi>p.</hi> 5. where the first Article is, <hi>A Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue between a</hi> Christian <hi>and a</hi> Quaker, <hi>yet made by</hi> T. Hicks. Judge now, whether this Man deserve <hi>Credit,</hi> who so little regardeth what he saith, that he boldly here affirms (and not only here, but in the Discourse it self most frequently) that <hi>the first Article against</hi> Tho. Hicks <hi>is for Opposing a</hi> Christian <hi>to a</hi> Quaker, and yet it appears <hi>by their own Book,</hi> that there is no such Sentence in that <hi>Article,</hi> no, nor in all the <hi>Charge</hi> besides.</p>
               <p>His next Reason is, <hi>Because many of the things</hi> T. Hicks <hi>hath charg'd upon the</hi> Quakers, <hi>were no otherwise true, but as they were the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequences of their being no</hi> Christians. This, <hi>Reader,</hi> is well worthy of thy Observation:
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:204828:50"/> for by this thou mayst plainly see how <hi>unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily</hi> these men have dealt with us, not caring what Way or Course they took, <hi>direct or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>direct,</hi> so they might thereby <hi>fasten Reproach</hi> and obloquie upon our <hi>Principles,</hi> Practices or Persons. <hi>Many of the Things charg'd upon us,</hi> he confesses, <hi>are no otherwise true, but as they are the Consequences of our being no</hi> Christians; yet these <hi>Consequences,</hi> like their <hi>forlorn</hi> Hope, were cast off long <hi>before,</hi> and the <hi>Antecedent was to come behind.</hi> Oh infatuated Men, and desperately Wicked! Could you <hi>without Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morse</hi> thus load an innocent People with <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famy,</hi> and pour out Floods of Reproach upon us, and now a Year or two after tell, that <hi>many of the Things, so charg'd upon us, are no otherwise true, but as they are the Consequences of another Proposition</hi> that is <hi>not yet prov'd!</hi> what else is this but, according to the Proverb, <hi>First to hang men, and then to try them?</hi> I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal, <hi>Reader,</hi> to thy impartial Judgment, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they have herein dealt with us <hi>as became Men,</hi> not to say <hi>Men of Religious Pretences.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Besides, I would have <hi>Jeremy</hi> know, that as the <hi>Design</hi> was <hi>dishonest,</hi> so <hi>his Logick is false</hi> (as I have else where noted) and can be of no other Use, then to prove the <hi>Ignorance</hi> or <hi>Malice</hi> of his <hi>Mind:</hi> for if it were <hi>possible</hi> for him to prove his <hi>Antecedent,</hi> that we are
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:204828:51"/> no <hi>Christians;</hi> yet his <hi>Consequences</hi> (having <hi>so long been accustomed to go before</hi>) will never <hi>by fair Means</hi> be brought <hi>to follow:</hi> But, if ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fair or <hi>foul</hi> will do, 'tis much alike to him.</p>
               <p>In his second <hi>Observation</hi> he tells the world, that <hi>we quibble about Words,</hi> and makes a Shew, as if he had gain'd some notable Advantage over us, in discoursing the Nature of a Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue▪ <hi>We charged</hi> T. Hicks <hi>with</hi> FORGERY, <hi>in calling his Book a Dialogue or Discourse be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween two, which never was a real Discourse be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween any!</hi> But, say they, Here is one of your own hath written in the same manner. No, say we, <hi>It is not the same Manner;</hi> for he doth not call his Book <hi>a Dialogue, but</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By way of Dialogue: that's the same thing say they; the terms are equivalent, said <hi>Jer. Ives,</hi> pag. 50. We deny it to be the same, or that the Terms are equivalent; and therefore <hi>Jeremy</hi> does but beg the Question, in supposing us to grant that which we do not. But that thou (Reader) may'st be able to judge, whether these two Cases be both alike, give me leave to state them both to thee according as they really are: One man writes a Book, and calls it <hi>simply A DIA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LOGƲE:</hi> In it he represents his <hi>own</hi> Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples <hi>as fair</hi> as he can, his <hi>Adversaries as foully;</hi> makes <hi>Answers in his Adversaries
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:204828:51"/> Name,</hi> as <hi>weak, silly, foolish, absurd, ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, impertinent</hi> and <hi>impious</hi> as possibly he can, <hi>conceals</hi> that this was <hi>written by him,</hi> and only sayes it was <hi>publisht by him;</hi> and he <hi>contrives</hi> and mannages the <hi>whole Design</hi> so, that his <hi>Reader</hi> may be <hi>perswaded,</hi> that he that pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lisht it, had <hi>no hand in the forming of it:</hi> but that those very <hi>Answers,</hi> how <hi>weak</hi> or <hi>wicked</hi> soever they be, were <hi>really so spoaken and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prest by that very Person,</hi> under whose Name they are set down: This is the State of the Case on the one hand. Another man writes a Book, and therein represents two or three Persons, <hi>as</hi> discoursing together; but that he may, <hi>at the very Entrance, secure</hi> his <hi>Reader</hi> from all <hi>Danger</hi> of <hi>Mistaking</hi> him, or thinking it to have been a <hi>Real</hi> Discourse, he tells him, it is written <hi>by way of Dialogue</hi> (which is <hi>after the manner</hi> of a Dialogue, or <hi>in Imitation</hi> of a Dialogue) and that <hi>he himself writ it:</hi> And this is the State of the Case on the other hand. The one of these doth but tell the World, <hi>what he thinks is my Opinion;</hi> the other intimates to the World, that <hi>I my self</hi> did <hi>speak</hi> and <hi>assert</hi> such or such a thing <hi>as my own Opinion,</hi> whenas I not only <hi>never so spoak,</hi> but also <hi>in my Heart abhor</hi> and detest the thing pretended to be so spoa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by me. Judge now impartial Reader, whether these two Cases be alike.</p>
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:204828:52"/>
               <p>But he adds, <hi>It is well known, that a Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue or Dialogismus is a Figure of Speaking, &amp;c.</hi> This is another of his <hi>sly Tricks,</hi> to slip in <hi>Dialogismus</hi> instead of <hi>Dialogus,</hi> and then <hi>insinuate</hi> as if a <hi>Dialogue</hi> and <hi>Dialogis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> were <hi>synonomous.</hi> But I will not spend Time on this; for I suppose no Reader that is <hi>capable</hi> of <hi>understanding Dialogismus,</hi> but will also be <hi>able to discern his Sophistry.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He goes on thus, <q rend="inline">
                     <hi>We told them, that <hi>Geo. Fox</hi> had writ a Discourse between a <hi>Papist</hi> and a <hi>Quaker,</hi> and did not say by way of Dialogue, or by way of Discourse, but a Discourse, which <hi>(sayes he)</hi> was never any real Discourse, but a feigned thing; and we offered to prove over and above, that he had abused and misrepresented the Person he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sents in his Discourse, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>That thou may'st the better understand this Passage, I desire thee, Reader, to look back with me into <hi>T. Plant</hi>'s Relation, pag. 54. where this Particular is set down by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves: J. Ives <hi>offers the Book, urges that it is called a Discourse. William Penn</hi> answers, <hi>I say it was a real Discourse, &amp;c. Jeremy</hi> replyeth, <hi>Then I require of you to prove it, That,</hi> sayes William Penn, <hi>I will do at ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time, but not now.</hi> At this they make the <hi>People hoot,</hi> and cry out, <hi>Prove it, prove
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:204828:52"/> it.</hi> Sayes William Penn, <hi>This is not fair, that instead of Answering our Charge against</hi> Thomas Hicks <hi>(the Cause of our Coming) you make a Charge extemporary against us, and give us no Time nor Paper of that Charge, and now call us to prove it, and the man is an Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Miles off.</hi> Could any thing be more <hi>ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous</hi> then for <hi>these men to triumph in a Hoot of the People</hi> (had that been true) because a thing that <hi>depended upon Personal Evidence,</hi> was not <hi>immediately</hi> proved, when we had <hi>not the least Notice</hi> beforehand of their Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to urge it, and <hi>the Evidence was an Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Miles off:</hi> But he sayes <hi>it was never any real Discourse, but a feigned thing.</hi> Well, though we are sufficiently <hi>able to prove it a real Discourse,</hi> yet seeing <hi>he is so rash and inconsiderate,</hi> I'le put him upon the <hi>Proof</hi> of his <hi>Affirmation,</hi> and give him Time for the doing of it too; <hi>let him prove it a Feigned Thing if he can.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But there is one Passage more to be taken notice of, before I pass from this Particular; He sayes, <q rend="inline">
                     <hi>We offered to prove over and above, that he had abused and misrepresented the Person he presented in his Discourse.</hi>
                  </q> How little doth this man <hi>consult</hi> the <hi>Credit</hi> of their <hi>Relation,</hi> or his own <hi>Reputation?</hi> I desire
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:204828:53"/> thee, Reader, to examine the place, pag. 54, 55. for I assure, I can find <hi>no such Offer at all</hi> exprest. Where lies the Fault <hi>Jeremy?</hi> Did <hi>some of you</hi> make this Offer, and yet is <hi>not</hi> in your Relation? <hi>Then your Relation is False in omitting it:</hi> Did <hi>none of you</hi> make this Offer, and yet hast thou <hi>affirmed</hi> you did? <hi>then thou art False in Affirming it.</hi> In short, <hi>Either</hi> (in this Particular) <hi>thou art True, and the Relation is False; or the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation is True, and thou art False;</hi> grant which thou wilt.</p>
               <p>In his third Observation he sayes, <q rend="inline">
                     <hi>That the <hi>Quakers,</hi> throughout both their Accounts of the two Meetings, make use of the <hi>vox po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puli</hi> to credit their Crazy Cause; sometimes telling the Reader, the People shouted, and other while hooted at the <hi>Baptists.</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </q> That this is the <hi>Fault</hi> themselves are <hi>guilty</hi> of, and therefore by Complaining <hi>anticipate</hi> our Complaint, let the following pages of their own Relation witness, pag. 49, 55, 57, 62, 79, 81, 82, 86, 88, 93, 94, 96, 97, 99, 102. in some of which <hi>they tell</hi> the Reader, <hi>the People laughed and shouted;</hi> in others, <hi>they shouted and hooted;</hi> one while, that <hi>they shouted extraordinarily;</hi> another while, that <hi>their Shooting and Hollowing was so extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:204828:53"/> that what was said could not be heard.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If <hi>Jeremy appeals to the People</hi> to vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate himself, <hi>he has them at his Beck;</hi> if he <hi>calls upon them</hi> to criminate us, <hi>they are forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with at his Devotion.</hi> What could the man desire more? or what indeed can be said more then this? That <hi>as his Brother</hi> Hicks <hi>had</hi> FORGED <hi>a Dialogue, and</hi> FORGED <hi>a</hi> Christian, <hi>and</hi> FORGED <hi>a</hi> Quaker, <hi>and</hi> FORGED <hi>Answers to his own Mind:</hi> So <hi>they have here framed a Relation,</hi> FORGED <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swers, and feigned a People Laughing, Shout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Hooting, Hollowing, when, how, and as often as they please.</hi> Nay, such a <hi>Knack</hi> hath <hi>Thomas Plant,</hi> that when he askt (pag. 49.) <hi>Is not this the First Article of the Charge?</hi> He can make the People cry, <hi>Yes, yes;</hi> though <hi>the Charge was not read unto them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But this is not all; <q rend="inline">
                     <hi>Another time <hi>(saith he)</hi> 'they tell the World, the <hi>Baptists</hi> made such a Noise with Laughing and Shouting, that they could not be heard. As if by this <hi>(sayes he)</hi> 'they designed to make the World believe they Hear as well as Speak by Inspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; otherwise how could they so curious<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly distinguish between the Voices of the <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tists</hi> and others.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>To pass by here <hi>his Ʋngodly Scoff at Inspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,</hi>
                  <pb n="106" facs="tcp:204828:54"/> let me ask him, <hi>how he knows</hi> they were <hi>Quakers</hi> that said, <hi>he did, he did,</hi> as their Relation sayes they were, pag. 50. and to the like purpose, pag. 57. It seems <hi>they could curiously distinguish</hi> between the Voice of the <hi>Quakers</hi> and others. But <hi>what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Ears</hi> may <hi>Thomas Plant</hi> be thought to have, that could <hi>so curiously distinguish Voices,</hi> as to <hi>discern</hi> the <hi>impartial</hi> from the <hi>partial</hi> Hearers, pag. 22. and not content to stop there, <hi>adventures</hi> also to tell the World, That <hi>the Answer was satisfactory to all the impartial Hearers?</hi> It seems he was <hi>so cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and quick of Hearing,</hi> that he could not only <hi>distinguish</hi> between the <hi>impartial</hi> and the <hi>partial,</hi> but <hi>could also tell</hi> (at least pretend so) <hi>when he had heard them all,</hi> though there were many Thousands of one sort or other.</p>
               <p>But he goes on thus, <hi>When one Mr.</hi> Nes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat <hi>in St.</hi> Martins, <hi>said of</hi> William Penn [What a Coxcomb is that?] <hi>they in their Account, pag.</hi> 22. <hi>tell the World, it was a</hi> Baptist <hi>that said so; which was both False and Malicious, as appeareth by a Certificate before re-cited, under the Person's Hand that spake the words.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This man is very apt to over-shoot himself: He sayes it was both False and Malicious, as
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:204828:54"/> appears by the Certificate, where the Certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficate sayes nothing of Malice; but only de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares, <hi>That the Subscriber of it is the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son who spake those words, that he is not, nor ever was a Baptist, and that the</hi> Quakers <hi>have lyed, in saying it was a</hi> Baptist <hi>that spake them:</hi> But as foul as they make him to fall upon the <hi>Quakers,</hi> yet he does not charge them with doing it Maliciously; that's <hi>Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my</hi>'s own Inference, thinking the other not foul enough. But as to this Shoe-maker in <hi>Martins,</hi> whatever he has been or is, his Expression was very Uncivil and Rude; and if he had not been an Adherent to them, or Favourer of them, it would have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come them to have rejected him then when the words were spoaken, and particularly taken Notice of: I desire the Reader there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to consider, 1. That this Shoe-maker was amongst them in their Gallery. 2. That he spoak these words in Defence of one of them. 3. That he spake so directly in <hi>Tho. Hicks</hi>'s Dialect, as if he had been his pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar Disciple. 4. That when some of the People called out, <hi>take Notice of that Man,</hi> the <hi>Baptists</hi> were silent, and did not discharge themselves of him. These things consider'd, I leave it to the Reader's Judgment, whether
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:204828:55"/> we had not some Reason to suppose the Person that so spake to be a <hi>Baptist.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In his 4th Observation he sayes, <q rend="inline">
                     <hi>That (by way of Reproach and Disgrace) we bring him in as one called an <hi>Arminian-Anabaptist,</hi> which by Interpretation is one that holds Ʋniversal Grace; and yet in the second Meeting we reckon it among the <hi>Anabaptists</hi> Errors, that they deny Ʋniversal Grace.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>I grant that he was brought in as one called an <hi>Arminian-Baptist,</hi> but <hi>not by way of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach or Disgrace to him</hi> (as he insinuates) but to shew how he, <hi>who holds Ʋniversal Grace,</hi> and his Brother Hicks, <hi>who denyes Ʋ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niversal Grace,</hi> could (like <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late</hi>) agree together to <hi>war against the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent;</hi> though <hi>their Judgments</hi> in that Point are as <hi>different</hi> as Light and Darkness, <hi>as op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posite as the two Poles.</hi> I also grant, That <hi>we reckon it among the Errors of some of the</hi> Anabaptists, <hi>that they deny Ʋniversal Grace:</hi> But what of all this? we not only reckon it as <hi>their Error,</hi> but as <hi>an Argument</hi> also of the <hi>Division that is among them;</hi> in that <hi>some of them</hi> (with Tho. Hicks) <hi>deny Ʋniversal Grace,</hi> while <hi>others of them assert it,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of <hi>Jeremy Ives</hi> is <hi>reputed</hi> one. But what doth <hi>Jeremy</hi> infer from his Observation?
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:204828:55"/> Why, <hi>that we are resolved to find Fault with any thing Right or Wrong.</hi> These are <hi>pittiful Shifts</hi> indeed! Dares he deny that there is <hi>this</hi> as well as <hi>other Divisions</hi> among them? Can he have the Face to say, There is not this <hi>plain Contrariety in their Creed!</hi> If not, to whom have we done Wrong? Why did he not tell his Reader where the Wrong lies? Is it in representing him as one that holds Universal Grace? Or is it in accounting those <hi>Baptists</hi> Erroneous that deny Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sal Grace? I wish the man would once learn to <hi>deal plainly,</hi> and not thus <hi>abuse his Reader.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In his 5th Observation he sayes, <q rend="inline">
                     <hi>In their Account of the <hi>Barbican Meeting,</hi> they tell the World, That in all that great Assembly there was scarce Breathing-Room allotted for above Twenty of them. This <hi>(sayes he)</hi> is most notoriously false; for they had a Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery of the same Dimensions with ours, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>This is the same in effect with what <hi>Thomas Plant</hi> had before observed in his Animadver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions on our Letter, pag. 36. of his Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; to which, having spoaken before, I shall not insist on it now: Only these two Questions I desire <hi>Jeremy Ives</hi> to <hi>answer ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestly to; First,</hi> Whether in all that great Assembly there was any more Room <hi>allotted
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:204828:56"/> for us,</hi> then that Gallery wherein we were? 2dly, Whether he himself does judge that Gallery capable of receiving above Twenty Men? And let the Reader then judge, whether we had not Cause to Complain; and whether our Complaint is not True.</p>
               <p>In his 6th Observation he sayes, <q rend="inline">
                     <hi>They so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly declare in their first <hi>Account, pag. 28.</hi> That with Reverence they believe, and confess to Christ, both as he is the Man Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus, and God over all, blessed forever, &amp;c. And yet <hi>(sayes he)</hi> they tell us in the same Page, That they are jealous of expressing their Faith in Ʋnscriptural Terms, as God-man, a Distinct Person without us (which limits and confines him to Remoteness) Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature of Christ in Heaven, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </q> Upon this he <hi>Cracks</hi> and <hi>Vapours,</hi> as if he had won some great Prize: But (Reader) let us examine the Matter, and if there be a Fault, see where it lies.</p>
               <p>We solemnly declare, That <hi>with Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence we believe and confess to Christ, both as he is the Man Jesus, and God over all, blessed forever.</hi> Well, is there any Fault in this? Not, unless a <hi>Socinian,</hi> or some other pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judiced Person be Judge. Where then lies the Fault? Let us search further: We are jealous of expressing our Faith in Unscriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:204828:56"/> Terms: Will they blame us for that? Have we not good Reason so to be? <hi>Of all men</hi> methinks <hi>they should not have censured us, for being jealous of expressing our Faith in Ʋnscriptural Terms, who themselves pretend the Scriptures to be the Only Rule of their own Faith.</hi> But what are the Terms we are jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of? <hi>God-man, a distinct Person without us (which limits and confines him to Remote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness) Human Nature of Christ in Heaven.</hi> Consider (serious Reader) whether such an Expression as God-man, according to the common and gross Acception of it, doth not tend to beget dark Imaginations, and mean, low, carnal Conceptions and Apprehensions of God, in the minds of ignorant People, who from such unscriptural Expressions have been too apt to fancy and represent God (as the <hi>Papists</hi> are said to paint him) an Old Man sitting in a Chair. Judge then who, deserves the Blame; they that make use of and impose such Terms as both give and continue the Occasion of such gross and wrong Apprehensions of the Deity; or we, who to prevent those wrong Apprehensions, chuse to express our Faith in the plain and Inoffensive Language of the Holy Scriptures.</p>
               <p>So for the Term, <hi>A Distinct Person with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out us, which limits and confines him to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moteness;</hi> we have very good Reason to be jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:204828:57"/> of it and avoid it, not only as an Unscrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural, but as an Unsound Expression; for, though we alwayes acknowledge, that Christ hath a Distinct Being without us, yet we can never yield that he is thereby limited and confined to a Remoteness from us: And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, how should we, when we daily feel him revealed and forming in us, to our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>speakable Joy and Comfort? I intreat thee (Reader) to consider seriously; Doth not the Scripture say expresly, <hi>Christ in you the Hope of Glory?</hi> Would not they now, who endeavour to limit and confine him to a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moteness, <hi>bereave both thee and me of this Hope,</hi> which is the <hi>Anchor of our Souls?</hi> And whither then shall we be driven? Did not our Saviour Christ himself, in that most Heavenly Prayer, which he offered to his Father, in behalf of his Disciples, a little before he suffered, express himself in these words: <hi>I in them, and thou in me, that they may be made perfect in One,</hi> Joh. 17.23. Was not this <hi>In-being &amp; In-dwelling of Christ in his Saints</hi> the <hi>Joy,</hi> the <hi>Crown,</hi> the <hi>Consola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of all <hi>true Christians</hi> in all Ages? And must we now be censured and <hi>unchristian'd</hi> for refusing such Terms as <hi>would limit and confine him to a Remoteness?</hi> Well, if the Case must needs be so, <hi>I'le rather chuse to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy his Living Presence with me</hi> (in whose
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:204828:57"/> Presence is Fulness of Joy) <hi>though I should therefore by them be reputed an</hi> Heathen, <hi>then purchase from them the Title of a</hi> Christian, <hi>at the Price of Confining him to a Remoteness from me.</hi> He was <hi>Emanuel</hi> of Old (<hi>God with us,</hi> or, as some read, <hi>God in us</hi>) <hi>O let him be</hi> Emanuel <hi>still!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But, what is the matter? Why do they quarrel so with us for avoiding <hi>such</hi> an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression as <hi>limits</hi> and <hi>confines Christ to a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moteness from his People?</hi> Would they have him <hi>so confined?</hi> Or, do they indeed think it <hi>possible</hi> that <hi>He</hi> should be <hi>so confined?</hi> Can they think so, and not at the same time <hi>deny his Divinity?</hi> for, <hi>as God,</hi> he is <hi>omnipresent,</hi> fills Heaven and Earth, and is <hi>not subject</hi> to any <hi>Confinement.</hi> If they say, they do not use such Terms with respect to his <hi>God-head,</hi> but only to his <hi>Manhood;</hi> I ask, With whom then do they quarrel? for, which of us did ever affirm, <hi>that Christ, in respect of his Manhood, is omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>present; or that as Man</hi> (in a carnal sense) <hi>he dwells in his Saints?</hi> Are they not then fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with their own Shadow?</p>
               <p>But while they thus <hi>captiously cavil</hi> at o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, they administer <hi>no small Ground</hi> of Sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pition, that they themselves, while they <hi>seem to confess</hi> the Divinity of Christ, do <hi>not really and cordially</hi> own it. For, let it be consider'd,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:204828:58"/> 1. That <hi>T. Hicks,</hi> in his first <hi>Dialogue, p.</hi> 44. saith expresly thus, <q rend="inline">
                     <hi>I told him that the Christ I believed, was no other then that Person the Scriptures speak of.</hi>
                  </q> 2. That <hi>they</hi> here <hi>blame us,</hi> for not expressing our Faith of <hi>Christ</hi> in such unscriptural Terms, as would limit and confine him to a Remoteness, which is <hi>not prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicable of the Divinity.</hi> 3. That <hi>J. Ives</hi> saith, (<hi>p.</hi> 23. of their Relation) that <hi>He was Christ as he was Man; not a Word of his Divinity.</hi> From these Premises let the judicious Reader judge what Conclusion may fairly be inferr'd.</p>
               <p>In like manner for the Term <hi>Human Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Christ in Heaven,</hi> may we not reasona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly be jealous of it? for if <hi>Humanus</hi> be deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from <hi>Homo,</hi> and that from <hi>Humus,</hi> which signifieth <hi>Ground</hi> or <hi>Earth</hi> (as the Learned tell <hi>us</hi>) would <hi>they</hi> have us <hi>say,</hi> that <hi>Christ hath in Heaven an Earthly Nature,</hi> whenas the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture saith so plainly, that it is <hi>the first Man that is of the Earth, earthly;</hi> but that <hi>the second Man is the Lord form Heaven,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.47. Let them therfore, before they so <hi>pragmatical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly censure</hi> others, declare to the World, what it is that themselves believe, <hi>if indeed themselves know what they believe.</hi> But to proceed.</p>
               <p>In his rambling Discourse upon this sixth Observation, he tells his Reader that we say, <hi>The Scriptures are not the Rule and Guide of
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:204828:58"/> Faith to the Saints;</hi> and for it he quotes <hi>Edw. Burrough</hi>'s Works, <hi>pag.</hi> 515. Reader, This is a Subject which hath of late been <hi>frequently controverted,</hi> between us and several of our Adversaries: Wherefore that I may not too far <hi>swell</hi> this Treatise, nor yet leave thee without <hi>some Means of Satisfaction</hi> how far, and in what respect we own the <hi>Scriptures</hi> to be a <hi>Rule, &amp;c.</hi> I refer thee to the following Books, <hi>Quakerism a new Nick-name for old Christia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, The Invalidity of</hi> John Faldo<hi>'s Vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>A serious Apology,</hi> &amp;c. in which this Subject is copiously handled. And for <hi>J. Ives</hi> his other Cavils about the <hi>Divinity of Christ,</hi> the <hi>Trinity, &amp;c.</hi> I refer thee to two Books, the one call'd, <hi>The Divinity of</hi> Christ <hi>confest and vindicated:</hi> The other, <hi>The Light and Life of</hi> Christ <hi>within.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Before I pass from this Particular, let me give thee, Reader, a brief Hint of <hi>Jeremy's</hi> unfair <hi>Dealing</hi> with us, in point of <hi>Quotation,</hi> which the Words last cited by him, out of <hi>Edw. Burrough</hi>'s Works, bring to my remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance. It is in a late <hi>Pamphlet</hi> of his call'd, <hi>Questions for the Quakers, p.</hi> 14. and the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of it this: <hi>Geo. Keith</hi> in the Dispute with <hi>Jer. Ives,</hi> asserted, that <hi>Divine Inspiration</hi> is the <hi>primary</hi> (or chief) <hi>Rule,</hi> and that the <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures</hi> are a <hi>secondary</hi> Rule. After this <hi>Jer.
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:204828:59"/> Ives</hi> printed his <hi>Questions,</hi> in which, <hi>that he might weaken</hi> Geo. Keith<hi>'s Testimony to the Scriptures,</hi> he brings in <hi>E. Burrough</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict <hi>G. Keith;</hi> and that he might <hi>make</hi> E.B. to contradict <hi>G. K.</hi> he <hi>most dishonestly falsifieth</hi> E. Burrough<hi>'s Words.</hi> Having premised this for thy better Understanding of the Passage, I will now, Reader, give thee <hi>J. Ives</hi>'s words, just as they lie in his own Book, thus; <q rend="inline">
                     <hi>For though <hi>G. Keith</hi> (to keep up your Credit) with the People, in our last Dispute) said, the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures were own'd by you as a secondary Rule for your Faith and Practice; yet <hi>E. Burrough</hi> contradicts him, and tells us in <hi>SO MANY WORDS,</hi> that the Scriptures are <hi>NO RULE</hi> or Guide of Faith and Life to the Saints. See <hi>(saith he)</hi> his Works, <hi>fol. 515.</hi> and reconcile your Prophets as well as you can.</hi>
                  </q> Now, <hi>Reader,</hi> take also <hi>E. Burrough</hi>'s words, just as they lie in the place forecited, thus: <q rend="inline">
                     <hi>And though the Scriptures are profitable, and were given forth to be read, and to be fulfilled, yet they are not <hi>THE RULE</hi> and Guide of Faith and Life unto the Saints; but the Spirit of God that gave forth the Scriptures, that is the Rule and Guide, the Teacher and Leader into all Truth.</hi>
                  </q> Now compare these two to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether: E.B. saith, <hi>The Scriptures are not</hi> THE <hi>Rule,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>J. Ives</hi> affirms, that <hi>E. B. in</hi> SO
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:204828:59"/> MANY WORDS <hi>saith, The Scriptures are NO Rule, &amp;c.</hi> and quotes this very place to prove it. <hi>O Impudent Man! O base and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honest Dealing!</hi> Is not this FORGERY? yea, and PERVERSION too: for he hath not only chang'd <hi>E.B</hi>'s <hi>Words,</hi> but his <hi>Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> also. What thinkst thou, <hi>Reader?</hi> Is this Man <hi>worthy</hi> of any <hi>Credit,</hi> who <hi>(to support a tottering Cause)</hi> will not stick to <hi>corrupt</hi> and <hi>falsifie another man's Words,</hi> and most <hi>audaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously</hi> tell the World, that that other man <hi>said so</hi> in SO MANY WORDS? And <hi>O ye</hi> Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tists, <hi>who have entertained and employ'd this</hi> Jer. Ives, <hi>as your Agent and Champion, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend you from the Stroke of our heavy</hi> Charge, <hi>consider ye well this thing! Think you to gain</hi> Credit <hi>by such a</hi> shameless Advocate, <hi>who, if he feared</hi> God, <hi>could not; and if he regarded</hi> Men, <hi>one would think he would not have publisht so</hi> FOUL <hi>and</hi> NOTORIOUS A FALSE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>HOOD <hi>to the World? Ah! Can you hope to stand your Ground, who so openly make</hi> Lyes <hi>your</hi> Refuge? <hi>The Lord will sweep away your Refuge, and where will you shelter then? Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely your Skirts are discovering apace, and your Nakedness appears already to many.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But to return to <hi>Jeremy:</hi> Much after the same Rate that he hath served <hi>E. B.</hi> doth he deal with <hi>G.W.</hi> also: For in p. 116. speaking
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:204828:60"/> of God and Christ, he sayes, That <hi>Father and Son are in the</hi> Quakers <hi>Dialect but two Names or Manifestations, as</hi> Geo. Whitehead <hi>calls them in his Defence of</hi> W. Penn <hi>against Dr.</hi> Owen <hi>and Mr.</hi> Vincent, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Herein he hath <hi>manifestly wronged</hi> G.W. both <hi>falsly citing and perverting his Words</hi> (And the better to cover his Falshood, he has neither directly named the Book, nor quoted any Page) for <hi>G.W</hi>'s VVords are not, that the Father and Son are BUT two Names or Manifestations; but thus, viz. That <q rend="inline">
                     <hi>the Three that bear Record in Heaven, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the Word and the Spirit, or the Father, Son and Holy Ghost, are one and inseparable, no where in Scripture called three separate Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, nor finite in Personalities, though three in Manifestation, and so testified of, as three Witnesses;</hi>
                  </q> See <hi>Divinity of Christ confest,</hi> part 2. p. 94. And <q rend="inline">
                     <hi>the Manifestation of the Father, of the Son and Holy Spirit we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fess,</hi> part 1. p. 22.</q> Now from <hi>G.W</hi>'s saying, <hi>We confess the Manifestation of the Father, of the Son and Holy Spirit,</hi> for <hi>J. Ives</hi> to infer that <hi>G.W.</hi> means the Father and the Son are BUT two Names or Manifestations; what is, if this be not, <hi>Perverting</hi> another Man's VVords? Yet he is not content with this, but goes on to abuse <hi>G. W.</hi> further; for sayes he,</p>
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:204828:60"/>
               <p>Geo. VVhitehead <hi>tells</hi> Mr. Vincent, <hi>that it is a distracted and confused Work to assert, that the Generation of the Son of God must be Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal.</hi> This also is a <hi>notorious Ʋntruth</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buse</hi> of <hi>G. Whitehead</hi>'s Words, as will plainly appear, if the Place be consulted: For upon Tho. Vincent<hi>'s saying, it is improper to say, that either the Persons in Regard of the Personality or Subsistence, are finite or infinite, yet that Christ is the Eternal Son of God by Eternal Generation: G.W.</hi> made an Observation thus, viz. <hi>He is now the Eternal Son of God, before not infinite: But again, neither finite nor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite in his Personality, and yet the Eternal Son of God: What mad, distracted, blasphemous Work is this,</hi> &amp;c? See <hi>Divinity of Christ confest,</hi> part 2. p. 74. This is no Denyal of the Son of God's being Eternal, but a Collection of <hi>T. Vincent</hi>'s Confusion about the separate Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonalities, as appears further in the same Book, <hi>part</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 24, 25. &amp; 34. Yet because G.W. having here gathered together some of his Opponents <hi>confus'd &amp; contradictory Discourse,</hi> did call <hi>it</hi> mad, distracted Work; <hi>J. Ives</hi> takes G.W<hi>'s</hi> VVords, and <hi>turns</hi> them quite to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Matter; G. W. called Tho. Vincent<hi>'s Manner of Reasoning</hi> about the Personality, Subsistence and Eternal Generation of the Son of God, <hi>mad and distracted Work; J. Ives</hi> reports <hi>G.W.</hi> to have said, <hi>That it's a distracted
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:204828:61"/> and confused Work to assert, that the Generation of the Son of God must be Eternal;</hi> whenas no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be more evident, then that G. W. condemned the <hi>Manner</hi> of asserting it, not the <hi>Assertion simply it self:</hi> What can a Man do more injurious to another, then so unfairly to misrepresent him, so fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>lly to pervert his Words and Meaning!</p>
               <p>In his 7th Observation, he taxeth the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts that we have given of the two Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and sayes, <hi>We have therein transplaced whole Paragraphs,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>to render his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swers Impertinent,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>But of this he gives</hi> us not one Instance, and we may well suppose the Reason to be, because he had not one to give. Besides, what Reason, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> so much as probable Conjecture, does he offer to his Reader, to induce him to believe this? None at all that I find: The most he sayes, is this, <hi>Whoever shall compare their Account and ours to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, will find it.</hi> But how will he find it? He must first take for granted, that their Account is true, which I have already by seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Instances <hi>proved to be false,</hi> and could there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to add several more, but that I judge those al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready given sufficient. Till therefore <hi>Jeremy</hi> sayes more to the Purpose, I shall not think this deserves more of my Notice.</p>
               <p>In his 8th Observation he tells his Reader, <hi>That in our Account we bring in many Things
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:204828:61"/> as spoken in their Presence, which were not spoaken till after their Departure.</hi> But where's the <hi>Evidence</hi> of this? The Reader hath but his bare Word for it, which how little Credit it deserveth I have shew'd before. But that which he infers from this <hi>is, That the</hi> Quakers <hi>could talk fast enough, when none were there to oppose them, though they stood like Mutes a little before, as having nothing to answer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This man is very frequent in his Suggestions, but it is rarely that he doth not <hi>contradict him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self</hi> in them. Let us see how he escapes in this: Here he insinuates, that <hi>we stood like Mutes, while he was present, as having nothing to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer;</hi> yet in <hi>p.</hi> 81. of their Relation, they say, <hi>Mr.</hi> Penn <hi>offer'd to interpose;</hi> and they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of <hi>two or three</hi> Quakers <hi>interposing to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</hi> In <hi>p.</hi> 82. <hi>Jeremy</hi> cries out, <hi>What, two or three against one man! What! Half a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen? You had best all speak.</hi> Again, <hi>p.</hi> 96. he saith, <hi>Pray Mr.</hi> Penn <hi>be silent; Pray Mr.</hi> Whitehead <hi>hold your Tongue, you are not to speak; it is not your Turn, &amp;c.</hi> And <hi>p.</hi> 102. when <hi>Jeremy</hi> had resolved to say no more, <hi>W. Penn</hi> calls upon <hi>Tho. Plant</hi> thus, <hi>Take</hi> J. Ives <hi>his place and I will proceed with thee.</hi> Observe, <hi>Reader,</hi> from these Quotations, how <hi>hard a Task</hi> they would make <hi>Jeremy</hi> to have <hi>undergone,</hi> to keep the <hi>Quakers</hi> from <hi>speaking
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:204828:62"/> too muh,</hi> so apt (it should seem) and <hi>forward</hi> they were to <hi>answer;</hi> and yet all on a sudden <hi>by a Figure peculiar to himself,</hi> he tells his Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, <hi>The</hi> Quakers <hi>stood mute in his Presence, as having nothing to answer.</hi> Thus, when men regard not <hi>Truth, Conscience</hi> or <hi>Honesty,</hi> they justly <hi>fall by their own Hands;</hi> and so it fares with these men: For in their Relation, their <hi>Design</hi> was to represent us <hi>clamorous, disor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly, talkative,</hi> speaking <hi>more</hi> then came to our Share (so in his <hi>Questions</hi> for the <hi>Quakers,</hi> p. 10. <hi>They talked most and talked last</hi>) Now in the Postscript <hi>the Scene is chang'd,</hi> and their Aim is now to represent us <hi>mute, silent, not able to say any thing for our selves;</hi> not consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering (though <hi>they took Time enough for it</hi>) that these two Suggestions would not well hang together, and now that they come to be examin'd, Shame <hi>(if they were not past it)</hi> would justly cover their Faces.</p>
               <p>In his 9th <hi>Observation,</hi> he quarrels at a Pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage in the Epistle to the <hi>Reader,</hi> prefixt to our Account of the 2d Meeting, which is this: <hi>We hope therefore thou wilt hold us excused in our honest and peaceable Endeavours to vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate our Faith and Persons against as black A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buses as have been ever practised by Infidels,</hi> Jews <hi>or</hi> call'd <hi>Christians:</hi> Here (according to his <hi>wonted Disingenuity</hi>) he <hi>quibbles</hi> upon the word <hi>Abuses,</hi> which <hi>(that he might thereby yet
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:204828:62"/> further abuse us)</hi> he would <hi>extend</hi> to the <hi>Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> the <hi>Apostles</hi> &amp; <hi>holy Martyrs,</hi> by which means he would <hi>hook in</hi> the <hi>Cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Torments</hi> &amp; various kinds of <hi>Death</hi> which they <hi>underwent,</hi> and then <hi>insinuate</hi> to his Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that we look upon the <hi>Abuses</hi> we have received from the <hi>Baptists</hi> to be <hi>blacker</hi> then the <hi>Sufferings</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> his <hi>Apostles</hi> and the <hi>Martyrs</hi> in Q. <hi>Mary's</hi> Dayes. In this his <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice</hi> is so <hi>apparent,</hi> that it needs no <hi>Detection:</hi> For what else but <hi>Malice,</hi> could so <hi>notoriously pervert</hi> our Sense and <hi>Meaning?</hi> which evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently related to <hi>such Abuses</hi> as we had char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged upon <hi>T. Hicks,</hi> viz. <hi>Forgeries, Perversions, Slanders, Lyes, Reproaches, Revilings, &amp;c.</hi> (of which <hi>J. Ives</hi> himself <hi>confesseth</hi> thus much, p. 45. That <hi>if our Charge against</hi> T. Hicks <hi>be true, he is the Prodigy of the Age for Lyes and Forgeries</hi>) not to <hi>corporal Sufferings, Torments, Death,</hi> as he would <hi>disingenuously stretch</hi> the word: Though we have too much Reason to <hi>suspect,</hi> that had they <hi>Power</hi> to their <hi>Will,</hi> we should quickly have as <hi>just Cause</hi> to complain of them in <hi>this respect,</hi> as we <hi>already</hi> have in the other; for <hi>they</hi> who, at this time of the Day, will take the Liberty publickly to <hi>repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent us</hi> not only as <hi>Blasphemers, Cheats</hi> and the <hi>vilest Impostors, Romish Emissaries,</hi> and most <hi>implacable Enemies</hi> to the <hi>Christian Religion;</hi>
                  <pb n="124" facs="tcp:204828:63"/> but also as <hi>Debauchers of Mankind, destructive to Government,</hi> and <hi>inconsistent with human So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety;</hi> and who are already entered <hi>a solemn League,</hi> as it were, with <hi>Independents</hi> &amp; <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians</hi> against us, need say no more to let us and the World know, <hi>what Kindness we might expect from them, if the Sword were in their Hands.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In his 10th Observation he saith, <hi>In many places in their last Book</hi> (especially in <hi>p.</hi> 60.) <hi>they tell the World, that instead of my proving them no</hi> Christians, <hi>I put them to prove they were</hi> Christians, <hi>which</hi> (saith he) <hi>is notoriously false, as the succession of my Arguments will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly manifest, if consider'd where the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sult and Issue.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For thy better Understanding of this Pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage, I refer thee, <hi>Reader,</hi> to the place he hath cited, <hi>p.</hi> 59, 60. of our Accout of the last Mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting; where his Arguments issue in this, <hi>If ye can give no Evidence of it, ye are</hi> no <hi>Christians</hi> (if he will deny this to be the Issue of his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, I am able to <hi>prove it</hi> out of <hi>their own</hi> Relation) Now, doth not the Rule of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traries infer, But <hi>if you can</hi> give an Evidence of it, <hi>ye are Christians?</hi> And doth not he o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver and over <hi>call upon us to give this Evidence?</hi> What then can be more plain, then that <hi>he calls upon us to give an Evidence that we are
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:204828:63"/> Christians;</hi> and is not this <hi>putting us to prove our selves</hi> Christians? Can he with all is <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilty</hi> spin a Distinction <hi>fine</hi> enough to h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>d be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Giving an Evidence that we are</hi> Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and <hi>Proving that we are</hi> Christians▪ If by the <hi>Medium</hi> that he hath taken, he would have prov'd us <hi>No Christians,</hi> he should not have <hi>put us upon giving an Evidence,</hi> but have <hi>prov'd</hi> we have <hi>No</hi> Evidence to give. If he say, he attempted to prove it by the <hi>Maxim</hi> in Law, <hi>That which appears not, is not:</hi> I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer; 'Tis true indeed that he did so <hi>attempt,</hi> but was <hi>pittifully foyl'd</hi> in his Undertaking: for it was shew'd him, that <hi>that Maxim would not hold true in all Cases;</hi> and <hi>himself</hi> soon af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter proved it <hi>false in this,</hi> when he acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged (<hi>p.</hi> 99.) <hi>that a dumb man may be a Christian</hi> (and consequently have the Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of it) <hi>yet not be able, because Dumb, to make that Evidence appear.</hi> If he say, that it being a <hi>Negative,</hi> there is no other way to prove it; I answer, he should have consider'd that <hi>before,</hi> and not have <hi>chosen</hi> such a medium, as he is <hi>not able to prove.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But (Reader) that thou mayest be assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that that which <hi>Jeremy Ives sayes</hi> is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriously false, is indeed most <hi>certainly true, viz.</hi> That being <hi>unable</hi> to prove us <hi>No Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians,</hi> he did put us <hi>to prove our selves Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians,</hi>
                  <pb n="126" facs="tcp:204828:64"/> and that too <hi>intentionally,</hi> take one Instance for all out of their own Relation, pag. 93. where <hi>George Keith</hi> having said, <hi>My Work at this present is not to prove our selves to be Christians;</hi> Jer. Ives <hi>taking hold</hi> of those words, replies pertly upon him, <hi>Why, what have we been disputing all this while for?</hi> plainly implying, that that which <hi>he</hi> had been <hi>disputing</hi> all this while <hi>for,</hi> was, <hi>to make us prove our selves Christians;</hi> and that if we did <hi>decline the proving our selves Christians,</hi> we did therein <hi>decline that</hi> which <hi>he</hi> had been all this while <hi>disputing for.</hi> Reader, I solemnly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, I would not, and indeed I think I have not <hi>strayn'd</hi> his words beyond their <hi>natural and proper Force:</hi> But whether I have or no, I leave to thy judicious Censure.</p>
               <p>In his 11th and last Observation, he sayes, <hi>Whereas they in their</hi> 2d Account, <hi>pag.</hi> 9. <hi>bid their Reader Note, That</hi> T. Hicks <hi>had lodged himself safely in an Ale-house, and came not to them, but stayed there till the Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates departing called him away,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>This</hi> (sayes he) <hi>is Maliciously and Falsly sugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Wherein doth it appear to be <hi>False</hi> or <hi>Malicious?</hi> Was <hi>Thomas Hicks</hi> in the Ale-house, or no? <hi>Yes, that he was: Jeremy</hi> grants it; but says, <hi>He was not Six Minutes
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:204828:64"/> there.</hi> I will not stand with <hi>Jeremy</hi> for <hi>a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute or two;</hi> but I would have him take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, that if <hi>Tho. Hicks</hi> had been but Three Minutes there, it had been enough to vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate our Relation from <hi>Falshood:</hi> But how long or little soever he was there, this is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that <hi>there he was, and there he stay'd, till some of them call'd him away:</hi> And how little it tends to his Reputation, to <hi>avoid the Meeting,</hi> and <hi>go to an Ale-house,</hi> I leave to the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der's Judgment. Yet in their Letter of <hi>Octob.</hi> 22. pag. 107. they would make the World believe, <hi>we seem to dread nothing more,</hi> then that <hi>T. Hicks</hi> should <hi>speak for himself,</hi> whenas <hi>he</hi> was not only particularly <hi>invited to the Meeting,</hi> but a Friend of ours going to the Meeting overtook <hi>T. H.</hi> in the way, and perceiving that he did not know either the Place or the Way to it, acquainted him that he was then going thither, and <hi>invited him</hi> to go along with him, telling him also, that probably he might be Wanted there: But <hi>T. Hicks,</hi> that he might not give a flat Denyal, urged an Occasion to call by the Way, and so <hi>declined</hi> the Offer. Judge now (Reader) whether their Suggestion be not <hi>false</hi> (not to say <hi>malicious</hi>) in saying, <hi>We seem to dread nothing more, then that</hi> T. H.
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:204828:65"/>
                  <hi>should speak for himself,</hi> when a Meeting was appointed by us for <hi>that End,</hi> and so much <hi>Endeavour</hi> used, and Care taken to get him thither, and yet he would not be perswaded to come there, but chose <hi>rather to go to an Ale-house.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In his last page <hi>J. Ives</hi> gives his Reader a List of One and Twenty Persons, whom he is pleased to call <hi>Sober Ministers,</hi> all who in an Epistle of theirs, jump in, and concur with him and his Brethren the <hi>Baptists,</hi> in their <hi>Clamour</hi> against the <hi>Quakers:</hi> For An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer to their Epistle, I refer the Reader to a Book of <hi>William Penn</hi>'s, entituled, <hi>A Just Rebuke to One and Twenty Learned and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Divines (so called)</hi> wherein I doubt not he will find their Strength <hi>sufficiently ener<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated.</hi> But I have not so done with <hi>Jeremy;</hi> I must take leave to <hi>expostulate</hi> the Case a little with him.</p>
               <p>How comest thou <hi>(Jeremy)</hi> to make use of the <hi>Testimony</hi> of these men, and dignifie them too with the Title of <hi>Sober Ministers?</hi> Hast thou forgot (or didst thou never know) that several of these thy <hi>Sober Ministers</hi> (particularly <hi>John Sheffeild, Thomas Gouge, William Jenkyn</hi> and <hi>Thomas Watson</hi>) were some of those <hi>Fifty Two London-Ministers,</hi>
                  <pb n="129" facs="tcp:204828:65"/> who in <hi>their Testimony to the Truth of Jesus Christ,</hi> and <hi>their Solemn League and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,</hi> printed Anno 1648. <q rend="inline">
                     <hi>Do testifie not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly their great Dislike of <hi>Prelacy, Erastianism, Brownism</hi> and <hi>INDEPENDENCY;</hi> but also their utter Abhorrency of <hi>Anti-scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rism, Popery, Arrianism, Socinianism, Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minianism, ANABAPTISM, Libertinism</hi> and <hi>Familism,</hi> with all such like, <hi>&amp;c. and that</hi> they Detest the Toleration so much pursued and endeavoured in this Kingdom, accounting it Ʋnlawful and Pernicious;</hi>
                  </q> yea, calling it not only <hi>detestable,</hi> but <hi>an hiddeous Monster,</hi> &amp;c. p. 33, 34. Dost thou observe, <hi>Jeremy,</hi> with whom they <hi>link and couple thee and thy Brethren,</hi> viz. with <hi>Anti-scripturists, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists, Arrians, Socinians, Libertines</hi> and <hi>Familists,</hi> and <hi>abhor you all alike?</hi> Were they <hi>Sober Ministers</hi> when they did this? Or are they grown <hi>more Sober</hi> since? And hast thou never heard that the <hi>Essex-Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters,</hi> men of the same <hi>Circumstances</hi> with these, dancing after their Pipe, did, in the same year, publish <hi>their Testimony</hi> also under the same Title with the former; wherein they say, <q rend="inline">
                     <hi>From our Souls we utterly Detest and Abhor, as all former Cursed Doctrines of <hi>Popery, Arminianism</hi> and <hi>Socinianism;</hi>
                        <pb n="130" facs="tcp:204828:66"/> so likewise all the Damnable Errors, Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies and Blasphemies of these present Evil Times, whether of <hi>Anti-scripturists, Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lists, Antinomians, Anti-Trinitarians, Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians, ANABAPTISTS, or whatsoever is found</hi> contrary to sound Doctrine and the Power of Godliness.</hi>
                  </q> Seest thou here, <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remy,</hi> how <hi>Thou</hi> and thy <hi>Brethren</hi> are <hi>rankt,</hi> and <hi>abhorred</hi> and <hi>detested</hi> by such as thou cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lest <hi>Sober Ministers,</hi> for <hi>your Damnable Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, Heresies</hi> and <hi>Blasphemies,</hi> as being <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to sound Doctrine</hi> and the <hi>Power of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liness?</hi> Would any but an <hi>infatuated</hi> man, have given an Occasion to revive such Testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies? Did ye <hi>fawn</hi> so on this sort of men then, and call them <hi>Sober Ministers?</hi> Or did ye repute them <hi>False Prophets, Seducers, Ministers of Antichrist,</hi> &amp;c? But how then came ye now so well <hi>reconciled,</hi> that ye can <hi>Rejoyce</hi> so in their Testimony? Have ye since <hi>Retracted those Damnable Errors, Heresies and Blasphemies,</hi> which they <hi>charged</hi> upon you, and for which they <hi>abhorred and dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted you,</hi> and submitted your selves to their <hi>Correction,</hi> that ye might be received again into <hi>Favour?</hi> Or have thy <hi>Sober Ministers</hi> cry'd <hi>Peccavimus,</hi> askt you Forgiveness, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o ye have kist, and are Friends? I would
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:204828:66"/> fain know how ye came thus <hi>reconciled;</hi> for methinks ye are too much like <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Pilate,</hi> who can so readily lay aside your <hi>mutual Grudges</hi> and <hi>Animosities,</hi> to bandy to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether against the Innocent.</p>
               <p>Or have ye learnt this <hi>Device</hi> of your One and Twenty <hi>Sober Ministers</hi> themselves, who so many of them as subscribed the above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Testimony, declaimed sharply a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst, and express their great Dislike of <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependency</hi> as well as others; though now to wage War against an <hi>Innocent People,</hi> they not only fall in and imbody with <hi>Independents,</hi> but have engaged as <hi>Voluntiers</hi> in Defence of <hi>John Faldo,</hi> a reputed <hi>Independent:</hi> By all which the Reader may observe how great a <hi>Confederacy</hi> and <hi>Combination</hi> is against us; and how they, who have formerly <hi>Anathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matized</hi> each other, now hug and embrace, fawn upon and <hi>Cajol</hi> one another into a kind of <hi>Solemn League</hi> against us.</p>
               <p>Now to let <hi>Jeremy</hi> and his Brethren see, how little Cause they have to <hi>boast</hi> of the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimony of their One and Twenty <hi>Sober Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters,</hi> I will here subjoyn the Names of those Fifty Two Priests, who testifie their <hi>Abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:204828:67"/> of the</hi> Anabaptists <hi>Errors,</hi> &amp;c. and their <hi>Detestation</hi> of <hi>Toleration.</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <item>Jo. Downame,</item>
                  <item>Peter Witham,</item>
                  <item>Fran. Roberts,</item>
                  <item>Arth. Jackson,</item>
                  <item>W. Wickins,</item>
                  <item>Elidad Blackwel,</item>
                  <item>Charles Offspring,</item>
                  <item>* JO. SHEFFEILD,</item>
                  <item>John Wallis,</item>
                  <item>John Fathers,</item>
                  <item>Ral. Robinson,</item>
                  <item>Chris. Love,</item>
                  <item>Tho. Cawton,</item>
                  <item>Joh. Glascock,</item>
                  <item>Matt. Hariland,</item>
                  <item>Nath. Stanyforth,</item>
                  <item>Tho. Whately,</item>
                  <item>* THO. WATSON,</item>
                  <item>John After,</item>
                  <item>Arth. Barham,</item>
                  <item>Jam. Cranford,</item>
                  <item>Andrew Janeway,</item>
                  <item>William Harrison,</item>
                  <item>* WILL. JENKYN,</item>
                  <item>John Wall,</item>
                  <item>Francis Peck,</item>
                  <item>Fulk Bellers.</item>
                  <item>Hen. Robrough,</item>
                  <item>* THO. GOUGE,</item>
                  <item>Ro. Mercer,</item>
                  <item>Samuel Clark,</item>
                  <item>Will. Taylor,</item>
                  <item>Geo. Fawler,</item>
                  <item>Ja. Nalton,</item>
                  <item>Will. Blackmore,</item>
                  <item>Geo. Walker,</item>
                  <item>Dan. Cawdrey,</item>
                  <item>Nich. Profett,</item>
                  <item>Antho. Tuckney,</item>
                  <item>Edm. Calamy,</item>
                  <pb n="133" facs="tcp:204828:67"/>
                  <item>John Stern,</item>
                  <item>Jos. Thomson,</item>
                  <item>Step. Watkins,</item>
                  <item>John Crodacott,</item>
                  <item>Will Gouge,</item>
                  <item>Tho. Gataker,</item>
                  <item>Sim. Ashe,</item>
                  <item>Tho. Case,</item>
                  <item>La. Seaman,</item>
                  <item>Stanley Gower,</item>
                  <item>Hen. Wilkinson,</item>
                  <item>Anth. Burgess.</item>
               </list>
               <p>I could here name above as many more of the same Tribe out of <hi>Essex,</hi> who concurred with these in their Testimony against the <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tists;</hi> But I think these may be enough for one time.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="134" facs="tcp:204828:68"/>
            <head>AN <hi>Expostulatory Postscript</hi> TO THE BAPTISTS.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>TO You the People called</hi> Anabaptists (of all Sorts) <hi>I direct the following Lines.</hi> How great a Controversie hath of late depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded (and yet doth) between us and some of the chief amongst you, I cannot supose you altogether ignorant, inasmuch as it hath not been debated in a Corner, but as publickly transacted as we could procure it, and made yet more publick by the Help of the Press: But whether ye have a right Understanding of the Nature and Subject of the Controversie, is questionable; For your better and fuller Information therefore, I will briefly and sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marily state it thus.</p>
            <p>T. Hicks, <hi>a Teacher among some of you, in</hi> several Books, which he hath printed and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Dialogues, <hi>hath most abusively and falsly represented our Principles and us to the World,
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:204828:68"/> perverted our Words and Meaning, published Lyes and Slanders against us, invented An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swers in our Names, impertinent, ridiculous and impious, and so contrived</hi> the whole Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that he might make the World believe, that <hi>these were indeed our own Words,</hi> and <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swers,</hi> and that they were <hi>really so spoaken</hi> by some of us, some <hi>Quaker,</hi> accordingly as he had there related them: For this <hi>we charge him</hi> with <hi>Forgeries, Perversions, Lyes, Slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> &amp;c. His Answer is, <hi>You are no</hi> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians; here he sticks and shelters himself, and is herein protected and defended by some of the <hi>leading Men</hi> amongst you.</p>
            <p>I demand now of those of you, who are most conscientious and honest in your Way, do your Hearts <hi>Justifie</hi> him &amp; them herein? Can you judge that he and they have dealt <hi>Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously</hi> and <hi>Equally</hi> with us? <hi>Would you be content to be so dealt with your selves?</hi> If I should write a Book against you, and therein <hi>abuse</hi> you, and <hi>falsifie</hi> your <hi>Principles, as he hath done us and ours,</hi> and should tell the World, that you your selves <hi>said</hi> this or that, or <hi>answered</hi> so and so, whenas indeed, you not only <hi>never said</hi> or <hi>thought</hi> so, but even <hi>abhor</hi> so to speak, and then instead of <hi>confessing</hi> my Fault, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>making you <hi>Satisfaction</hi> for the <hi>Injury,</hi> should only tell you, that <hi>ye are no</hi> Christians, would
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:204828:69"/> ye not think your selves <hi>highly wronged,</hi> and account me a very <hi>Wretch</hi> for doing it? Oh be <hi>just,</hi> be <hi>just,</hi> and suffer not <hi>so great a Blemish</hi> to lye upon your <hi>Profession.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Consider seriously, I intreat you, if what they say of us were true <hi>(then which nothing can be more false)</hi> that we were not <hi>Christians;</hi> would that <hi>extenuate</hi> his <hi>Crime,</hi> or any Way excuse him for having so grosly <hi>belied and abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed</hi> us as he has? Does your Religion give you Liberty to <hi>invent</hi> and <hi>publish Forgeries, Lyes and Slanders</hi> against those that you account No <hi>Christians,</hi> and to <hi>pervert their Words and Meaning?</hi> How much <hi>better</hi> then is <hi>our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion</hi> then <hi>yours,</hi> which will not <hi>suffer us</hi> to <hi>deal</hi> so with a <hi>Jew,</hi> a <hi>Turk,</hi> an <hi>Infidel,</hi> no, nor the <hi>worst</hi> of Men? Surely if this be the <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude</hi> of your Religion, it is high Time for all the <hi>honest-hearted</hi> among you, to <hi>quit it, quit it,</hi> as fast as they can.</p>
            <p>We demand nothing of you but <hi>Justice</hi> against your <hi>unjust Member;</hi> and will ye by <hi>denying</hi> us that, <hi>involve</hi> your selves in his <hi>Guilt,</hi> and <hi>entitle</hi> your selves to his <hi>Crimes?</hi> O <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware, beware;</hi> will ye <hi>shelter</hi> a Man under the <hi>Wing</hi> of your <hi>Profession,</hi> who stands charg'd with such <hi>foul</hi> and <hi>abominable Evils,</hi> and dares not <hi>adventure</hi> himself upon <hi>Tryal</hi> but studyeth <hi>Shifts</hi> and <hi>Tricks</hi> to <hi>avoid</hi> it? Let him first,
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:204828:69"/> if he be able, <hi>acquit</hi> himself of the <hi>Forgeries, Perversions, Lyes</hi> and <hi>Slanders,</hi> which lye, as so many <hi>Indictments</hi> against him; and when that is done, let him and his Adherents put forth their <hi>utmost Strength</hi> and <hi>Ability,</hi> to prove, us No <hi>Christians;</hi> we are not fearful of a <hi>good Issue,</hi> but ready and willing, with an holy Confidence, to encounter them <hi>all,</hi> in Defence of our <hi>Christianity;</hi> nay, have we not twice already <hi>condescended (though beside the Business, and out of its proper Season)</hi> to hear them say the <hi>utmost</hi> they were <hi>able</hi> upon that Subject, until themselves <hi>were weary of it, and withdrew?</hi> And what Advantage they have <hi>gain'd</hi> thereby, we are well content the World should judge.</p>
            <p>But after all this, shall we have <hi>no Right</hi> done us? must we be <hi>continually</hi> calling upon you for <hi>Justice?</hi> It is now much about two Moneths Time, since I sent forth a <hi>single Sheet</hi> under the Title of a FRESH PURSUIT, &amp;c. In which I gave a succinct Account of the Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion, Rise and Progress of this Controversie, briefly also touching (by the way) some of those <hi>Devices, VViles</hi> and <hi>Artifices</hi> which our Adversaries have used to <hi>divert</hi> us from the <hi>Prosecution</hi> of our <hi>Charge,</hi> and <hi>turn the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troversie into another Channel:</hi> Which having done, I <hi>re-inforced</hi> our Charge against <hi>T. Hicks</hi>
               <pb n="138" facs="tcp:204828:70"/> and his Abettors, and took upon me to <hi>make it good</hi> against them before a Publick and free Auditory: But inasmuch as they have taken no Notice of it, I think fit to reprint that Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragraph wherein our Charge is re-inforced; The Words are these:</p>
            <p>In Pursuance of which Resolution, <hi>I,</hi> who am one of the People called <hi>Quakers, do here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by</hi> on the behalf of my Brethren and my self, <hi>publickly re-charge the said</hi> Thomas Hicks <hi>with many foul</hi> Forgeries, <hi>gross</hi> Perversions, <hi>notorious</hi> Falshoods, Slanders, <hi>and Defamatory</hi> Expressions, <hi>by him published against the</hi> Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers <hi>in his fore-mentioned Books; which</hi> Charge <hi>I take upon me to make good against him, before a Publick and free Auditory. And I do hereby also charge all those his Brethren</hi> (whose Names are subscribed to a Book of theirs, call'd, <hi>The Quakers Appeal answered, together with their Champion</hi> J. Ives, <hi>with being accessory to the said</hi> Forgeries, Perversions, Slanders, &amp;c. <hi>in favouring, countenancing, abetting or defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the said</hi> Tho. Hicks <hi>therein:</hi> And <hi>this Charge I fix and leave upon all their Heads, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til Justice be publickly done us herein; which I do hereby solemnly demand of the whole Body of the</hi> Baptists <hi>throughout this Nation</hi> (many of whom, I am perswaded, own not such Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice) <hi>as they will answer it before the just God,
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:204828:70"/> and in the Heart of every Ʋpright Man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>Charge</hi> I now <hi>re-iterate,</hi> and the same <hi>Demand</hi> of <hi>Justice</hi> I now again <hi>solemnly make,</hi> an earnestly <hi>press</hi> it upon <hi>all</hi> such among you, as are any whit <hi>tender</hi> and <hi>conscientious</hi> in your Way, and <hi>at your Door I leave it.</hi> The Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons charg'd are some of your own Members: <hi>Do us Justice; do us Right;</hi> bring them to the <hi>Test;</hi> let them <hi>acquit</hi> themselves if they can; if not, let them <hi>sink</hi> under their own <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den;</hi> but do not you, by <hi>adhering</hi> to them, or endeavouring to <hi>protect</hi> them, <hi>draw their Iniquity upon your own Heads.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>T. E</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>Page 11. Line 24. for <hi>must</hi> read <hi>may'st.</hi> p. 35. l. 3. f. <hi>Equum</hi> r. <hi>Aequum.</hi> p. 41. l. 12. dele <hi>the stop</hi> (,) after <hi>say.</hi> p. 46. l. 21. f. <hi>adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> r. <hi>add we were.</hi> p. 52. l. 5. of the Margi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Note, f. <hi>he</hi> r. <hi>we.</hi> p. 54. l. 16. f. <hi>Ran</hi> r. <hi>Van.</hi> p. 70 l. 23. f. <hi>or reject</hi> r. <hi>and reject.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>